<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mirrour or miracle of Gods loue vnto the world of his elect Preached on the third of Iohn, verse the sixteenth: wherein the said scripture is very learnedly expounded, and the rich treasures of Gods grace in Christ are accurately opened. By that faithfull seruant of Christ, and preacher of his Gospell, Mr. Paul Baine.</title>
            <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101581</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837390</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837390</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1709</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1709)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 912:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mirrour or miracle of Gods loue vnto the world of his elect Preached on the third of Iohn, verse the sixteenth: wherein the said scripture is very learnedly expounded, and the rich treasures of Gods grace in Christ are accurately opened. By that faithfull seruant of Christ, and preacher of his Gospell, Mr. Paul Baine.</title>
                  <author>Baynes, Paul, d. 1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 70, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for Nathanael Newbery: and are to be sold at his shop vnder St. Peters Church in Cornhill, and in Popes head Alley, at the signe of the Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The mirrour of Gods loue, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>Final leaf contains: A pillar, erected on the graue, and inscribed, to the deere memory of that learned and godly diuine, Mr. Paul Baine. By I.E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1709:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1709:1"/>
            <p>THE MIRROVR OR MIRACLE OF GODS LOVE VNTO the world of his ELECT. PREACHED ON THE third of <hi>Iohn,</hi> verſe the ſixteenth: Wherein the ſaid Scripture is very lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly expounded, and the rich treaſures of Gods grace in CHRIST are accurately opened. By that faithfull ſeruant of Chriſt, and preacher of his Goſpell, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PAVL BAINE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 5.8.</hi>
               </bibl> But God commendeth his loue towards vs, in that while we were yet ſinners, Chriſt died for vs.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 8.32.</hi>
               </bibl> He that ſpared not his owne Sonne, but deliuered him vp for vs all: How ſhall he not with him alſo freely giue vs all things?</q>
            <p>London, printed by <hi>H.L.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery:</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop vnder S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornhill, and in Popes head Alley, at the ſigne of the Starre. 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1709:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1709:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL SIR <hi>THOMAS ROBERTS,</hi> KNIGHT, and the very worthy Gentleman, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Walter Roberts,</hi> his Sonne and heire; with all externall comforts, the eternall bleſſing of GODS loue in CHRIST.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat ſome rich men, who are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues childleſſe, with good proofe &amp; comfort doe, in bringing vp the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane child of ſome deceaſed friend; the ſame, or ſome ſuch like thing haue I aſſaied to do in the publiſhing of this Sermon. I my ſelfe goe child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe for any publike birth of mine owne braine: nor is that any griefe vnto me. There is no need (I well perceiue) of my ſlender helpe in this kinde, either <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this ſuperfluitie of vſeleſse pamphlets, (to ſay no worſe of them) wherewith our age ouerflowes; or in this ſtore (which to the glorie of Gods grace in our daies, and iust praiſe of their authours, I
<pb facs="tcp:1709:3"/> acknowledge) of well meant and well deſeruing labours. And what need ſoeuer there were, I am too weak an <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las</hi> to vphold this firmament.<note place="margin">Authores non o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet libros ſed theſauros compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere. Domiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſo.</note> 
               <hi>Writings of Author<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth one well) <hi>ſhould bee, not ſo much bookes packt vp with paper, and blackt ouer with inke, as Treaſuries repleniſht with variety of choyſeſt learning:</hi> Nor (as I conceiue) empty coffers filled with the fome and fume of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle heads, nor dead mens coffins pestered with the rotten carrion of prophane, filthy, and corrupted hearts, nor olde chests ſtuffed with ruſty iron, thread bare rags, and refuſe geare; but rich cabinets, at whoſe opening the Reader might finde ſtore, new and old, of the beſt and rarest things which <hi>Canaan, Greece,</hi> or <hi>Rome</hi> doth yield. With which varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I do too well know, that it is beyond my ſcant ſtore to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the table, and entertaine my gueſts. I am therefore well content to ſit ſtill, and chuſe rather to feed vpon the ſweet and wholeſome hony which other industrious Bees gather and bring vnto the hiue, applauding their well furniſht and well poliſht works; then to come vpon the publique ſtage to do that which needs not, or attempt that which I cannot, either with iust ſhame for my Bayardlike boldnes, or euen from the moſt fauourable, with more pity for my well mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then prayſe for my well deſeruing. Notwithſtanding, lighting vpon this Sermon of that both learned and godly Diuine, <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Paul Baine</hi> (of whoſe gracious ability in prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Gods word, ſomtime your owne eares, &amp;, I perſwade my ſelfe, your harts alſo were witneſſes) as a poore orphane babe of a deceaſed friend, as for the memory of its Author, which will euer be deare vnto mee, I did gladly embrace and entertaine it: ſo induced by the example of others, who with good acceptance and ſeruice to the Church, publiſh both
<pb facs="tcp:1709:3"/> larger Treatiſes and briefe Sermons of his making; I haue ventured to ſhew my ſelfe ſo farre on this Theater, as to ſet it forth to publike view, and make it common vnto others with mee. Wherein good men, I preſume, will both ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept my good meaning, to doe that for them by the labours of other men, which I cannot by mine owne (that is to ſet forward their knowledge in the great myſterie of godlineſſe) and conne mee thanke, who haue ſet vp for them ſuch a faire and cleere light, to diſcouer that abſtruſe myſtery, and to light them onward in that way. For, there is ſcarce in the Book of God, a Mine that is more rich and aboundant in diuine metall and myſtery, then the Text handled in this Sermon. In which at one viewe, as in a cleere mirrour, there is preſented to vs the fountaine (Gods eternall loue) from which all good bleſsings iſſue and flowe forth vnto vs; the common ciſterne (Ieſus Chriſt, the onely begotten of God, beſtowed on vs) in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al theſe bleſsings (as al wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the Sea) are gathered together, and incloſed; the bucket (Faith) whereby wee may draw out of this Well whatſoeuer grace wee doe neede; Laſtly, the moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſweet waters, which are heere in plentifull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for vs to draw and drinke of: that is, euerlaſting bliſſe and ſaluation of ſoule and body. It is much then to bee wiſhed, that as this Scripture is familiar in the mouthes of many; ſo the myſteries thereof were well vnderſtood and cloſe applied to their hearts. Whereunto this Treatiſe, I dare promiſe, will affoord ſome good helpe to thoſe that will deigne diligently to peruſe it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For, herein the foreſaid points are diſcuſſed and diſcourſed, with that equall mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of learning and pietie, that both the learned ſhall meete with ſome things not very common perhaps not to increaſe,
<pb facs="tcp:1709:4"/> yet to renew his more ſecret knowledge, and whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his iudgement; and alſo the godly Chriſtian ſhall not vvant wherewith to feede his deuouteſt meditations, and enkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle his beſt affections toward God.<note place="margin">Landat ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>les qui vult extru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>remer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. <hi>Horat.</hi>
               </note> But leaſt I doe ſeeme like ſome deceitfull Broker, to ſet worth on worthleſſe wares, by goodly words; I will leaue the proofe hereof to your owne, and the iudgement of other Chriſtian, and not faſtidious Readers. Onely (good Sir) giue mee leaue to ſend it abroad vnder the ſhield and ſhadow of your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips name; and in the patronage thereof, to aſſociate with you your very worthy ſonne. I could not well ſeparate you in this ſmall office of kindneſſe, whom nature hath ioined ſo neerely by the ſecond of her ſtraiteſt bonds; and much goodwill in ſundry fauours, haue made ioint partners and patrons vnto mee.<note place="margin">Fulmen Lauri frut. cem non icit. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> Your two names, as a Laurell Garland wreathed on the fore-front heereof, this Sermon, will (I truſt) helpe to guarde it from the blaſting of euill tongues; or like the fortunate Starres of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 37.</note> when they appeare double, giue hope of the more ſecure paſſage, vnto it. It is a Worke, I am ſure, that will well beſeeme your gentleneſſe, To patronize this Posthume Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane; nor can it bee any blemiſh to your reputations, To lend your countenance to the child of ſo good a man. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept therefore (much reſpected Sirs) this ſlender preſent which I offer you, as the best acknowledgement which I can make of your conſtant loue and kindneſſe, whereby I haue had ſpeciall comfort in the place where I liue. It were happely more credit for mee to make this whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſatisfaction out of mine owne ſtocke: but it will bee your greater gaine, that I doe it out of anothers purſe: Mine owne would proue but ſhort pay, and copper coine;
<pb facs="tcp:1709:4"/> whereas what heere I haue borrowed to tender vnto you, is currant and pure gold of Gods ſanctuary: which, if it pleaſe you to put it vp, will adde ſome good increaſe to your ſpirituall treaſure of ſauing knowledge. What on my part is wanting in performance, I will make vp with my harty deſires and prayers for your proſperous ſtate in the world, and ſpirituall welfare in the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At the Free-ſchoole in <hi>Cranebrooke</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> 
                  <date>December the <hi>14. 1618.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips, in all Chriſtian ſeruices, <hi>J. E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1709:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1709:5"/>
            <head>THE MIRROVR OR MIRACLE OF GODS LOVE VNTO THE WORLD OF HIS ELECT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IOHN 3.16.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For God ſo loued the world, that hee hath giuen his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him ſhould not periſh, but haue euerlaſting life.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is no wiſedome to bee compared with the knowledge of God in Chriſt.<note place="margin">The excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Chriſt.</note> This hath not a few Arguments to commend it. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.3. It is not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply wiſedome, but Gods wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in an eminent and high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, wrapped and folded vp in a myſterie which all men cannot conceiue. It is a ſecret hidden wiſedome: and that not lately deuiſed, but thought on of old, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued and decreed by God, euen before his purpoſe to create the world, for a more ſpeciall aduancement vnto glory. Yea, to know God in Ieſus Chriſt is life it ſelfe that life which is euerlaſting: which it bringeth vs not onely in a ſure hope and expectation; but in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1709:6"/> ſome fruition of it, in the foretaſte and firſt fruits ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. I haue therefore made choice of this place, as in which both God our louing Father, and Chriſt the gift of his grace are vnfoulded vnto vs. But before we come to handle the words themſelues, it is fit by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing their coherence, to know the true ſcope they aime at, and if any thing bee obſcure to vnfould it.<note place="margin">The coherence of the words.</note> The dependance they haue on the former words is on this ſort; Chriſt in the verſe immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly going before gaue this out generally: That whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer beleeueth ſhall haue life euerlaſting. Now the Iewes giuen to emulation, might thinke much that the priuiledge of life ſhould bee communicated with the vncircumciſed Gentiles. Chriſt therefore meeteth with this corruption,<note place="margin">Which come in to meete with a ſcandall of the Iewes.</note> and confirmeth the vniuerſality of that propoſition, with this reaſon. What GOD propoſeth as his end, ſhall certainely be. My counſell ſhall ſtand, and I will do whatſoeuer I will. <hi>Iſay</hi> 46.10. But God hath ſet downe with himſelfe this end in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his Sonne; that whoſoeuer beleeueth ſhall haue life: <hi>Ergo</hi> Whoſoeuer beleeueth ſhal haue life euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The Minor is in theſe words of my Text: the concluſion in the fifteenth verſe: the propoſition is from elſewhere to be gathered and ſupplied. In the words there is onely one phraſe of ſpeech that doth neede to be vnfoulded; that is, what is meant by the <hi>world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Their ſenſe.</note> 
               <hi>Theophylact</hi> giueth two ſignifications of this word,<note place="margin">What is meant by the world.</note> in the eleuenth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> the one <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, the whole vniuerſe. The other, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, men worldly minded. Some taking it in the former ſenſe very largely,<note place="margin">Not all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome thinke.</note> though not for the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſalitie of the creature, yet for all men vniuerſally,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1709:6"/> giue theſe two interpretations of it. The firſt, thus. God ſo loued all men, that he vouchſafed to giue and offer his Sonne in the preaching of the Goſpell vnto all; according to thoſe places: <hi>Goe, teach all Nations, Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Preach the Goſpell to euery creature. Marke</hi> 16.15. A trueth, I confeſſe, but not meant in this place. For heere is not meddled with the Miniſterie: but the Decree of God, and manner of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is manifeſted. And when wee come to handling of thoſe words of giuing the onely begotten, we ſhall ſee that agreeably vnto the context, they are to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in another ſenſe. The ſecond expoſition is, that God ſo loued all, that hee gaue his onely Sonne to death, of purpoſe and effectually for all. But this is falſe. For euen this one reaſon ouerthroweth it.<note place="margin">For God did not purpoſe the ſaluation of all mankinde by Chriſt.</note> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Lord purpoſed, Chriſt perfectly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. <hi>I haue finiſhed the worke thou gauest mee to doe. Iohn</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7.4. But Chriſt did neither make interceſsion, nor dye for all. <hi>Ergo.</hi> The firſt is proued: <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.9.<note place="margin">Since Chriſt did not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede for all mankinde.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. I pray not for the world.</hi> That is, ſay ſome, not that they ſhould continue in worldly courſes. <hi>Anſ.</hi> There is an oppoſition betweene the world, and thoſe that were giuen vnto Chriſt; which plainely ſheweth that hee doth exclude the world from the benefit of his prayers, as being none of thoſe which were giuen him by his Father: which oppoſition doth alſo inferre and inforce thus much, that if in one member (as, for them which thou gaueſt me) perſons, namely Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect are meant, as is moſt euident: then in the other we are to vnderſtand not worldly courſes, not appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God; but men, paſſed by &amp; neglected of him.</p>
            <p>But this prayer is not made by him as Mediatour.<note place="margin">Euen when he prayed as Mediatour.</note>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:1709:7"/> 
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſh ft is vtterly ouerthrowne by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of this Chapter. For this was made when the houre of his offering vp approached; was as it were the ſanctification of himſelfe thereunto; was not made for a few godly, but all that euer ſhould beleeue, <hi>verſe</hi> 20. Which <hi>Cyril</hi> ſaith to be put in, leaſt that the high Prieſt and Mediatour of our ſoules ſhould not ſeeme to intercede for vs.<note place="margin">Pontifex &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatar animaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> noſtrarum pro nobis minime interrogare videretur.</note> And the iudgement of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril</hi> is, that he maketh this prayer as Mediatour on the ninth verſe of this Chapter. Where hee hath theſe words; <hi>Chriſtus ſuos a non ſuis ſeparans, pro his qui verbum audierunt, qui iugum ſuſceperunt, rogat, quorum Mediator atque Pontifex eſt, iſtis tantummodo mediatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis bonum non iniuria attribuens:</hi> that is, Chriſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating his from thoſe that were not his, doth pray for thoſe which heard his word, which had taken his yoke on them, not vniuſtly beſtowing the benefit of his mediation onely on thoſe, whoſe Mediatour and high Prieſt he is.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Not did die for all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, but his ſheepe onely.</note>The ſecond thing, that he died not for all, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. <hi>verſe</hi> 15. <hi>I lay downe my life for my ſheepe.</hi> Yea, but may it be ſaid, all are his ſheepe. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Not ſo. For his ſheepe haue their note and name giuen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em of ſeparation from others which are not ſo: Secondly, in the twenty ſixt <hi>verſe</hi> hee ſaith to ſome preſent, that they were not of his ſheepe. That is, wilſome ſay, becauſe they would not beleeue. <hi>Anſ</hi> Nay rather becauſe they were not his ſheepe, they beleeued not, as there appeareth. And at the laſt iudgement we ſhall know that there is difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt goates and ſheepe.</p>
            <p>Some third ſignification then is to be inquired:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1709:7"/> which wee ſhall ſee by comparing 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.14. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. to be the people of God whom hee ſaueth in the world, and to note no more. Hee is the Sauiour of the world,<note place="margin">But it noteth Gods people in the world.</note> ſaith <hi>Iohn:</hi> and who or what is this world that he ſaueth? All men? Not ſo, but his people: as in <hi>Mathew</hi> is expounded; <hi>Thou ſhalt call his name Ieſus: For he ſhall ſaue his people from their ſinnes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Which all are not.</note> But all are Chriſts people <hi>Anſw.</hi> If his Kingdome of power be conſidered, it is true: but not ſo of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of grace. His people in this regard are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, <hi>Tit</hi> 2.14. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.<note place="margin">But onely the Elect.</note> to bee a peculiar and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen people. Diuers Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers call the diſpenſation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Chriſt <hi>Oeconomia,</hi> which noteth a domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call regiment ouer the houſ-hold of faith. And thus <hi>Auſten</hi> often conſtrueth the word world; <hi>pro mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſeruandorum, mundo redemptionis.</hi> For the world of the ſaued ones, the world of the redeemed, to which is oppoſed, <hi>mundus damnandorum et perditionis;</hi> the world of the damned or loſt wretches. And ſo on the ſeuenteenth of <hi>Iohn, verſe</hi> 23. that the world may know, &amp;c. Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is, ſaith <hi>Camerarius</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe which are ſaued in the world.<note place="margin">Called the world for three cauſes.</note> And there are three reaſons why the Church of God, the bodie of Chriſt which only belongeth to ſaluation, is called by the name of the world. 1. They haue their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vniuerſalitie. For all kindes, and all times haue made vp this number. Secondly, now the fulneſſe of time approached that the Church was to become Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique, in regard of place. The whole world after a ſort was to goe into it: not the Iew and Grecian on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but euen th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scythian and Barbarian too. Thirdly, in reſpect of their ſtate, before they are effectually
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1709:8"/> called, and actually made the ſonnes of God. For before this they walke after the courſe of the world. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.2. So then, the true meaning of theſe words is this. God ſo loued his people choſen to ſaluation through the world, that he gaue his Sonne, that they ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting. The which vvords fitly caſt themſelues for matter into theſe three points.<note place="margin">Three points of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 1. The ſpeciall loue of God toward his. <hi>God ſo loued the world.</hi> Secondly, the effect of his loue, <hi>that he gaue his onely begotten Sonne,</hi> Thirdly, the end, <hi>that whoſoeuer beleeueth in him might haue life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlasting.</hi> Firſt, I will giue the inſtructions which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues to our conſideration in the two firſt members. Secondly, I wil come and peruſe the words more particularly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> I. God doth beare a ſpeciall loue to his.</note>The firſt doctrine is intimated in the firſt word, <hi>So. So God loued the world.</hi> For heere is inſinuated ſo much: That the Lord regardeth his with an eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fauour. To vnderſtand this the better, wee muſt ſee how the compariſon ſtandeth. God loueth all his creatures, and hateth (as the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> ſpeaketh) no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing he hath made. For to loue, is nothing but to will well, and to doe well to any. Now the Lords goodnes is ouer all.<note place="margin">God is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally good to all creatures. More ſpecially to Man.</note> For in him we liue, euerything hath life, motion, and being from him. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.28. He doth preſerue the very beaſt. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 36.6. But much aboue all other creatures doth hee loue mankinde. The arguments whereof are;<note place="margin">Foure ſignes thereof.</note> Firſt, his long ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance toward vs: Secondly, his indulgent grant of the vſe of his creatures, whereof we haue made our ſelues iuſtly vnworthy. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.17. Thirdly, that Chriſt took not the nature of Angels, but hath aſſumed into one
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1709:8"/> perſon with his Godhead the ſeede of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Fourthly, that hee doth vouchſafe the Goſpell of his Sonne to all mankinde. But though his mercie is ouer all, and aboue other creatures ſhewed vnto man: yet the loue vvherewith theſe are embraced,<note place="margin">But his loue toward his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect is moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire &amp; aboue al.</note> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vvith that loue wherewith he hath his children accepted through Chriſt, is called hatred: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore CHRIST ſetting down this, doth by this word <hi>(So)</hi> make a diſtinction of this kindneſſe and loue from all other.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> who ſounded deepely both our miſerie in our ſelues, and happineſſe in Gods loue, when hee commeth to conſider this loue to his in CHRIST, doth raiſe his ſtile, as if no vvords were ſufficient to expreſſe it: as may bee ſeene, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.6. But ſpecially <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.4. &amp; 7. where this his kindneſſe toward vs in Chriſt, is called great loue, rich mercie: Yea, and more, the excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding riches of Gods grace.<note place="margin">Moſt rich.</note> And ſpeaking of Gods loue in Chriſt (for this and the loue of Chriſt, becauſe God was in Chriſt, may and doth ſound all one: as <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. The queſtion being asked, Who ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of Chriſt: The anſwere is, nothing ſhall ſeparate vs from the loue of God which is in Chriſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 39. making them to bee the ſame) ſpeaking, I ſay, of this loue, he doth wiſh, the <hi>Epheſians</hi> might be able to know the ſame, though indeed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing knowledge.<note place="margin">Paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> 
               <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.19. where he maketh it to be a loue inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible, much more vnſpeakeable. It is therfore compared with the loue of a Father. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 103.<note place="margin">Moſt affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</note> 13. <hi>As a father hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſsion on his children; ſo hath the Lord compaſsion on them that feare him.</hi> And preferred before the moſt tender bowels of a mother. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.15.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1709:9"/> 
               <hi>Can a woman forget her childe, and not haue compaſsion on the ſonne of her wombe? Though they ſhould forget, yet I will not forget thee.</hi> And as it is moſt rich and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, ſo it is a loue no leſſe ſure and conſtant:<note place="margin">And conſtant.</note> for it hath for its ground onely the good pleaſure of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11.15. and therefore ſhall neuer change, nor can be altered.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Vſes. 1. From gods loue to vs we muſt learne the loue of our brethren</note>For the vſe hereof; Firſt, Gods example in morall duties is euery where made to vs a patterne of imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>Be ye holy, for I am holy.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.26. Wee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from this loue of God toward vs, muſt learne to loue one another, as <hi>Iohn</hi> doth vrge it on vs, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.11. Beloued, if God loued vs, nay, ſo loued vs, that is, with ſo admirable and ſuperaboundant loue, wee ought to loue one another: For what? are wee too good to loue there where God himſelfe doth loue: and that with maruellous loue aboue all creatures? or doth God beſtowe ſuch ſingular loue on any man, who is not thereby made worthy of our loue? As no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doth more become a ſort of beggers children whom ſome rich and noble perſon ſhould ſo loue as to adopt them his ſonnes and fellow-heires, then to loue dearely and intirely among themſelues: ſo is it a moſt ſeemely thing that we ſhould follow God in this loue, and imbrace them with true and feruent loue whom he hath made fellow-heires with vs; yea, and in our loue we muſt keepe the ſame order which the Lord obſerueth; <hi>Be yee mercifull as your Father is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Our loue ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble Gods for kinde and order.</note> 
               <hi>Luke</hi> 6.36. ſaith our Sauiour. As the ſame mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is to be ſhewed by vs not for meaſure &amp; degree, but for kinde, which God ſheweth: ſo muſt wee tread the ſame ſteps for order, wherein our heauenly Father
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1709:9"/> doth goe before vs. There is no creature ſpecially of thoſe that are ſeruiceable to vs, but we muſt be louing and kinde thereto.<note place="margin">Shewing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to beaſts, more to men: moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the godly.</note> A righteous man doth regard the life of his beaſt: <hi>Prou.</hi> 12.10. Next, all men muſt be loued: but as God doth embrace his elect with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular loue aboue other men; ſo muſt wee be more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially affectioned toward the godly, as <hi>Paul</hi> doth direct vs, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Doe good to all men, but eſpecially vnto them which are of the houſ-hold of faith.</hi>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2 Our loue to God a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> neighbour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> get<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rom Gods loue to vs.</note> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this point touching Gods loue toward vs, doth ſhew whence it is, that our loue to God &amp; our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is engendred; euen hence doth it proceed from Gods louing of vs. Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.12.16. doth proue and conclude that wee are in God, and haue the knowledge and faith of Gods loue to vs, euen from our loue to God, and our Brethren. For God is loue: yea, that maine and vaſt ſea of loue, from whom all thoſe ſtreames and riuelets of loue that are in men do iſſue and flowe.</p>
            <p>If vvater bee vvarme and doe heate,<note place="margin">We are this way key cold vnleſſe God warme vs.</note> it is not of it ſelfe (for it is an extreame cold element) but by vertue of fire in ſome ſort dwelling in it, which the Philoſopher cals the exceſſe of heate: So the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue of God and our brethren, cannot kindle of it ſelfe in our hearts, which are moſt auerſe there from, but muſt come from God, who is loue himſelfe, dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and reſiding in vs, and our taſte of this infinit fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vnto vs. As Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith plainely, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.19. that we loue God, and ſo our neighbours, becauſe he loued vs firſt. The cold and frozen earth cannot cheriſh the trees and plants with any kindly heate and iuice, except it firſt bee thawed and warmed with the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1709:10"/> aſpect of the ſunne ſhining on it, and approaching to it. And ſo the loue of God looking out vpon vs in Ieſus Chriſt, muſt firſt melt our frozen, and warme our cold hearts, before we can ſhew and put forth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny affection, or worke of loue to God and our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Nor is this point needleſſe to be knowne.<note place="margin">A point need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to bee knowne.</note> For if we know it not, we ſhall neither giue praiſe to God vvhen this affection ſparkleth in vs: nor know when it is frozen whither to repaire, that it may bee reuiued and inflamed in vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. The folly of the world, which hateth moſt whom God loueth.</note>Thirdly, from this loue of God to his, we may take notice of the folly of the world. For they hate there moſt, where the Lord loueth moſt. <hi>I</hi> (ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.14. <hi>haue giuen them thy word, and the world hath hated them, becauſe they are not of the world, &amp;c.</hi> The more loue God doth manifeſt vnto any in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them his word and grace, to obey and imbrace it, the more the hatred of the world doth boyle and breake out againſt them. Water for the contrarietie that it hath with fire,<note place="margin">A note of their comitie againſt God and the godly.</note> doth hiſſe, ſpet and ſputter, not onely vvhen fire falleth into it, but if any thing throughly heated with the fire catch it. And whence is this in worldly men, but from their aduerſe diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to and hatred of God, that they hate the deareſt people of the Lord, and thoſe in whom his grace is moſt apparant? In Princes Courts are not they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious ſpirits and fooliſh men,<note place="margin">And the next way,</note> that profeſſe open and mortall hatred to the greateſt Fauorites of the King? Doe they not take the right way to ruinate themſelues and their eſtates? Such as are politiquely wiſe, and intend to riſe to any matters or eſtate in the Court, will rather obſerue the Kings ſpeciall fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1709:10"/> loue them, and inſinuate into their acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: So is it a moſt ſottiſh folly in men of the world, to hate the Lords holy and deare children. For be they ſure that the Lord vvill hold them (as they are) ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to him;<note place="margin">to k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ep th m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from all bleſsings.</note> that they ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l want many a ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sing from the King of Heauen, which the prayers of the godly vvould obtaine for them. Yea,<note place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to ruinate themſelues.</note> many plagues will light vpon them in this reſpect. If they will be wiſe for their ſoules and bodies too, it is their beſt vvay to loue and embrace with all kindneſſe the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, which God vvould take as a token of loue to himſelfe, and they ſhould haue the benefit of their prayers, vvhich can obtaine great things from God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It followeth, that he gaue his onely begotten Sonne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Doct. 3. Gods deareſt loue is manifeſt not in outward things, but in Chriſt giuen vs.</note>OBſerue heere wherein the ſpeciall loue of God conſiſteth: not in health, wealth, honours, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, libertie, and ſuch like, but in the gift of Chriſt. As his loue towards his was exceeding great, yea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite; ſo hee had no better way to euidence this loue, but by the gift of his Sonne. By this therefore doth the word of God in ſundry places commend to vs the loue of God. God ſetteth out his loue vnto vs (ſaith <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 5.8.) <hi>that while we were ſinners, Chriſt died for vs.</hi> So 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.9. <hi>In this appeared the loue of God toward vs, becauſe God ſent his onely begotten Son into the world, &amp;c.</hi> God did manifeſt and magnifie his loue in nothing ſo as in the gift of his Sonne vnto vs: All his other loue in diſtributing vnto vs wealth,<note place="margin">No other loue at he laſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it.</note> libertie, honour and pleaſures, is more then we are
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1709:11"/> worthy of: but it h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d beene poore and cold loue in reſpect of any good and comfort to vs-ward, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt giuen vs. Wherin therfore doth <hi>Paul</hi> place, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.7. the exceeding riches of Gods grace and kindneſſe, but in Ieſus Chriſt? that is, in this that he hath giuen vs Chriſt: without whom notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the worlds good and glory,<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> we moſt miſerable.</note> there is no brute beaſt, nay, there is not the vileſt and baſeſt creature on the earth, but it is in more happy ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on then we are.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Vſes.</hi> 1 We erre to doubt of Gods loue vnder the Croſſe.</note>The vſe of this briefely is, to take away the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall of the Croſſe, and comfort vs therein. For vvee, when euill doth whip vs, the Croſſe lies heauy on vs, and ſome bitter cup is meaſured out vnto vs morning by morning, beginne to queſtion Gods loue, and thinke that vvee are not beloued of him. But wee goe by a vvrong line, and falſe rule. For wee muſt looke off from theſe things, and examine whether hee hath giuen CHRIST vnto vs or no. If wee finde this onely begotten Sonne reuealed in vs,<note place="margin">Specially if wee know &amp; haue Chriſt,</note> wee may then aſſure our ſelues, that vvee are loued of GOD, and that euen with this ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all loue.<note place="margin">Who is the ſole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt of Gods loue.</note> CHRIST is the ſureſt, yea, the onely pledge of Gods loue; whom, if wee haue beſtowed on vs, let other matters goe as they may, wee neede not to doubt, but that wee are of Gods beſt and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt fauourites.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. They dream who preſume on Gods loue for their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritie.</note>Secondly, this may ſerue to quell and pull downe that vaine prefidence that is in many: vvho, vpon the bare enioyment of outward things in great plenty, preſume themſelues to bee moſt deepely in the Lords fauour, and before others in that point.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1709:11"/> For this is a moſt fond preſumption and meere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion, to build our hopes of Gods loue, on ſuch ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die grounds. No man can know whether GOD loue or hate him by theſe outward things, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.1.<note place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uffe without Chriſt they are but as traitours with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Pardon, frolick ng it by the King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> patience.</note> Were it not fond for a Traitour to preſume of the Kings Mercie that hee doth let <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im in the Tower take his reuenues, enioy his Lady and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, ride his great Horſe, and vſe what Lordly ſports hee pleaſe? Can any thing aſſure him of this gracious mercy of his Prince, but his pardon ſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him vnder the Kings hand and Seale? So haue thou as much of this vvorldly happineſſe as thou canſt wiſh: be thou for outward things the mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and enuie of the vvorld, yet art thou neuer the farther in the fauour of GOD. Thou ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt but as a condemned Traitour before him, vnleſſe thou finde that hee haue giuen CHRIST vnto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, to bee thy peace and thy attonement. Onely ſo farre as thou haſt the knowledge of of this Iuſt One imparted to thee, as thou do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt loue him and his Goſpell, as by faith hee is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thine; ſo farre canſt thou haue any aſſurance of Gods loue and mercy.</p>
            <p>All other things notwithſtanding,<note place="margin">No better th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cain.</hi>
               </note> without Chriſt giuen to thee, it is no better with thee then <hi>Cain</hi> or <hi>Iudas,</hi> nay, then vvith the Diuell himſelfe,<note place="margin">Nay, then the Diuell.</note> who is the Prince of the world, and hath the glory and happineſſe of it aboue the greateſt Monarch of the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Doct. 3. God doth loue his, before Ch iſt be giuen to die for them.</note>Thirdly, ſince God out of loue to his, giues Chriſt for their redemption, obſerue that there is a loue of God to his now in miſery, before Chriſt himſelfe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1709:12"/> in as Mediator for them. Loue, though in God it is but one moſt ſimply, as himſelfe is moſt ſimply one:<note place="margin">
                  <p>Gods lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e twofold.</p>
                  <p>A latter enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſts de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th.</p>
                  <p>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nifeſt in our iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation.</p>
               </note> yet for the change that it maketh in the creature, and to help our weake vnderſtanding, a former and a latter loue and grace may be conſidered. For there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth a grace of God vnto vs from the bloud of Chriſt, in which mercy this new teſtament of giuing to vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing iuſtification vnto life, is ſtricken. Therefore Chriſt is called <hi>the Mediatour of the new teſtament. Heb.</hi> 9.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.24. his bloud, <hi>the bloud of the newe teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Mat.</hi> 26.28. And of this grace, that place in the third to the <hi>Romanes, verſe</hi> 24. may bee vnderſtood, where the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>wee are iuſtified freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">And reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> And in this reſpect the ſcripture putteth our reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation to God, in the death of Chriſt. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.25. and elſewhere. But now theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces muſt not be ſo vnderſtood, as if the Lord within himſelfe before entirely hated vs; but therefore theſe phraſes are vſed, becauſe that in Chriſt that former loue of God ſpringeth forth, which while iuſtice was vnſatisfied, might not bud out, but lay hid and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched.<note place="margin">A former loue ſhewing it ſelfe in the gift of Chriſt.</note> For there was a loue to vs before Chriſt, of which here is ſpoken; and the effect whereof, the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of Chriſt himſelfe, is heere affirmed. A kinde-hearted father doth oft beare a ſecret and inward affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction toward an vngratious ſonne, whom he hath caſt out from him: as <hi>Dauid</hi> toward <hi>Abſalom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.39. &amp; 14.1. &amp;c. though he will not ſuffer it to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, till by the ſuit and requeſt of ſom friend whom perhaps himſelfe ſuborneth, he bee reconciled to his ſonne: no leſſe was there in God a hid loue toward vs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1709:12"/> before Chriſt, which the Lord would not ſuffer to break forth to our knowledge, till Chriſt by his death had made our peace for vs. Neither need we feare the putting of contrary wils in God by this meanes:<note place="margin">Before whom God was eſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged from vs in regard of ſin: but did loue vs as foreknowne of himſelfe.</note> for though, as we were in a ſort our owne worke through ſinne, in regard of iuſtice hee did ſtand ſeparated and eſtranged from vs; yet as wee were his worke, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as he had of his gratious pleaſure foreknowne vs, he loued vs, and in loue elected vs, and therefore no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hindreth, but that his immutable fauor in theſe reſpects might be ſtill continued toward vs, and ſo it was. For as his iuſtice for ſinne held vs vnder wrath and death: ſo his loue worketh another way, taking vs out of the hand of iuſtice by giuing his only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, in whom iuſtice and mercy doe kiſſe each other. And to ſay that the Lord altogether hated vs in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, vntill Chriſt made interceſſion, is ſuch an aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as we ſhall be eaſily inforced to reuerſe. For Chriſt made intercesſion, called or vncalled: if called, there was great loue in the Father, calling him to do ſuch a kinde office for vs. If we ſay vncalled, we goe againſt the Scriptures of the old and new teſtament, in which nothing is more euidently taught then the calling, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing, and the ſending of the ſonne by God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">The vſe to commend Gods loue as very antient.</note> This now ought to make Gods loue the more deare and pretious vnto vs, as being very antient, and freely borne toward vs: antient I ſay, for we are loued of God before Chriſt was appointed our Mediatour, <hi>who yet was ordained before the foundation of the world.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20. Wherefore Gods loue hath been toward vs from all eternity. Now loue, as wine, doth receiue the greater prayſe by the age of it: old wine is the beſt
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1709:13"/> and antient loue is the moſt approued. How much doe we eſteeme of ſuch a friend as hath borne vs good will for ſome twenty or fourty yeares together? The more reckoning ſhould we make of Gods loue, which hath been eternall. Then alſo it is moſt free;<note place="margin">And moſt f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee.</note> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt wee were enemies to God, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be ſeene in vs but ſinne and miſery, nor any thing to draw Gods affection toward vs, but his own free and good pleaſure: now that loue which we haue deſerued, we the leſſe eſteeme; but ſuch loue as is free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conferred on vs, we do make more ſtore of. And this is the excellency of Gods loue vnto vs, that it is moſt free and gratious; no way procured by our ſelues who were children of wrath; no nor by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the firſt motion of it: but it did giue Chriſt as a pledge thereof, and a meane to make way more plen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ifully to poure out it ſelfe vpon vs. Fourthly, <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. Doct. Our redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Chriſt doth beſt of all manifeſt Gods loue.</note>Whereas God louing vs giueth Chriſt vnto vs, wee are to obſerue that this courſe of redeeming vs by Chriſt is moſt anſwerable &amp; agreeable with the loue and grace of God. True it is, if Gods abſolute power be conſidered, and the freedome wherewith hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to all, which from eternity he decreed, we may ſay,<note place="margin">Another way was poſſible, but this moſt fit.</note> hee could haue taken another courſe for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption. But if a way be conſidered wherein his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pecially his loue might be made manifeſt, this is of all moſt fit and expedient. For it followeth (as he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re you ſee) on Gods loue, as if loue it ſelfe had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned it, and he hath choſen this way: who as hee is moſt powerfull; ſo is not his wiſdome any whit infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to his power. And that this point may bee the more cleared, as alſo that we may ſee that when <hi>Paul</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:1709:13"/> falleth into the argument of Gods loue, hee doth not without cauſe ſpeak ſo loftily, we will ſift theſe words ſomewhat more narrowly.<note place="margin">Setting ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods loue in foure circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Wherein foure circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are to be noted, whereby the loue of God is much amplified. Firſt, the partie louing: Secondly, thoſe that are loued: Thirdly, the thing giuen: Fourthly, the manner of giuing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, in this that God loueth,<note place="margin">1. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> who firſt ſought loue, when wee gaue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt offence.</note> his exceeding grace is not a little commended. For when two men are at variance, if the partie wrongfully offended do ſeeke him, who gaue him the offence, how is his meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and gentleneſſe thereby declared? Euen thus the caſe ſtandeth twixt God and vs: we had prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked his diſpleaſure; he procureth our reconciliation and attonement. And for this cauſe our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Redemption is ſaid to be made of God to vs. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> alſo expending and weighing this thing, doth from it magnifie the loue of God. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.10. <hi>In this is loue, not that wee loued God, but that he loued vs.</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">2. In the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons loued: v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>z. our ſelues being ſinners, &amp; his enemies.</note> to conſider the perſons loued, is no leſſe argument, whereby this loue may be extolled For who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loued God? Vs, ſaith <hi>Iohn.</hi> Being now like the world, no better then the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates; when our deeds, words, and wiſeſt thoughts were enmitie againſt him; then I ſay, did God regard vs. From hence <hi>Paul</hi> bringeth in the loue of God moſt gloriouſly cloathed, ſaying, that it was great loue and rich mercy in God, that he did then quicken vs, when we were dead in ſinnes and treſpaſſes. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.4.5. And <hi>Romanes</hi> 5.7 from hence alſo doth hee extoll it. In this God ſetteth out his loue vnto vs, that when we were his enemies, Chriſt died for vs. The third
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1709:14"/> circumſtance is the thing giuen,<note place="margin">3. In the thing giuen: viz the onely begotten Sonne of God.</note> &amp; that is in this word, the only begotten: which is a vvord putting a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt this perſon, and any other. Euery where in Scripture excellent priuiledges are beſtowed on Gods children: but ſo that Chriſt hath ſtill the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence. Wee call God Father, as Chriſt teacheth vs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.9. and this Abba Father is the voice of the Spirit which is in vs. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 6. Yea, ſo did the Church, when this ſpirit of adoption was not ſo plentifully powred out. <hi>Iſay</hi> 63.16. Thou art our Father, though <hi>Abraham</hi> be ignorant of vs, and <hi>Iſrael</hi> know vs not. But Chriſt calleth God, as the Iewes rightly gather, <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.18. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, his owne, his proper father,<note place="margin">Vnto whom God is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per father.</note> in ſuch a ſort as no man elſe did or could; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they would not ſo haue ſtormed at him. So wee by nature are the ſonnes of wrath, yet by faith we haue this priuiledge to be the ſonnes of God. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. But Chriſt is called his owne proper Sonne,<note place="margin">He is Gods proper Sonne.</note> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. who ſpared not his owne Sonne. So, we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten not of bloud, nor of the will of the fleſh, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.13. but God of his owne will by the word of trueth hath begotten vs. <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.18.<note place="margin">And one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: Not becauſe of the ſtrange fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature. As <hi>Seruetus</hi> falſely.</note> But Chriſt is the only begotten euen from the Father. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14. Where by the way, we may not vnfitly conſider <hi>Seruetus</hi> his expoſition, who ſaith, that Chriſt is ſaid the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of God onely in regard that his humane nature was framed in a ſort proper to himſelfe. But this is but a fiction. For firſt, conſider what it is to beget, and Chriſt cannot in regard of the humane nature be ſaid begotten. To beget, is <hi>ex ſubstantia gignentis proferre ſimile ſecundum ſubſtantiam,</hi> that is, Out of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the begetter, to bring forth a like thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1709:14"/> to its ſubſtance. But now the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and diuine eſſence are wholly different. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he ſhould rather in this reſpect be the onely begotten of the holy Ghoſt. For that perſon imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and determinatiue, did frame of the ſubſtance of the Virgin, that immaculate maſſe, and vnite it to the diuine nature. Thirdly, <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> might thus as well be ſaid the onely begotten of God, who were after a proper manner made of God. Fourthly, Chriſt as man hath alwaies beene held as without fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and <hi>(ergo)</hi> vnbegotten. For theſe two ſtand in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation one to the other. Fiftly, the Scripture auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth this phraſe, ſaying of Chriſt, <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.14. that he was made fleſh; and <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.3. made of the ſeede of <hi>Dauid:</hi> and <hi>Galathians</hi> 4.4. made of a woman. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſometime vſed; but it ſignifieth nothing but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be borne: <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.1. and ſo <hi>Ialad</hi> is vſed anſwerably with the Hebrew. If this <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> bee further vrged, as it may, it muſt bee onely to proue that Chriſt was not <hi>in Maria</hi> onely, but <hi>ex Maria</hi> alſo, againſt <hi>Marcion.</hi> So then if you aske what this thing borne in and of the Virgin was, I anſwere, the onely begotten Sonne of God. If you aske how; I anſwere;<note place="margin">But becauſe of the perſonall vnion of it with the onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne.</note> not becauſe the humane nature vvas thus ſtrangely framed, but becauſe it was perſonally vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the onely begotten of God. Now then wee may fitly come to conſider what this is that God beſtoweth; in a word, his only begotten made fleſh, God with vs. <hi>Immanuell.</hi> A great gift.<note place="margin">A wonderfull gift:</note> For the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after a ſort hath giuen himſelfe. For he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen that perſon, in whom he is wholly, and who alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether is in him. But if wee will view the rich pieces
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1709:15"/> in this Iewell, what rare matter can we wiſh, which is not heere included? Wee are (as <hi>Zophar</hi> ſpeaketh) borne like wilde Aſſe colts. <hi>Iob</hi> 11.12. Would wee haue wiſedome?<note place="margin">Wherein we haue wiſdome,</note> Heere is the eſſentiall wiſedome of the father, the obiect of all true wiſedome, which tendeth to ſaluation: yea, in him is our wiſedome, not onely while wee walke by faith at home in this body, but alſo when we ſhall walke by ſight with the Lord, ſeeing him as hee is. All the treaſures of wiſedome and vnderſtanding are hid in him: <hi>Col.</hi> 2.3. Would you haue Righteouſneſſe?<note place="margin">Righteouſnes,</note> Hee is eſſentially righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as God; in our nature habitually and actually righteous: He is <hi>Iehouah</hi> our righteouſneſſe, the Sunne of righteouſneſſe, that perſon which hath brought with him euerlaſting righteouſneſſe. Would you haue Redemption?<note place="margin">Redemption,</note> With him is great redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.7. Through him haue wee redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is, forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes: <hi>Col.</hi> 1.14. By him wee doe waite for the redemption of our body: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. and laſtly ſhall haue the redemption of the inheritance purchaſed vnto the praiſe of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.14. Would you haue Sanctification?<note place="margin">Sanctification,</note> He is our ſanctifier. The ſpirit is giuen to him, not by meaſure, that wee might draw from him grace for grace. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.34. &amp; 1.16. The fulneſſe of the Godhead dwelleth perſonally in him, that in him we might bee compleate. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 1.9, 10. Which place ſpeaketh not ſo fitly of any thing imputed to vs, as of thoſe graces which from him are infuſed. Would you haue life?<note place="margin">Life,</note> Hee is the reſurrection and the life: <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.25. Both the firſt and ſecond reſurrection come from him: And we doe not now liue, but it is
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1709:15"/> Chriſt who liueth in vs; <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.20. Yea, euery parcell of that glorious life wee leade in the heauens muſt come from him. For this life is hid with Chriſt. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.3. Would you haue any thing? Why this onely begotten is heyre of all things;<note place="margin">and plenty of all things for ſaluation.</note> thoſe that beleeue on him, are coheires with him, and haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to that new heauen, and new earth which ſhall ſtand before the Lord for euer. Hence it is that the Church ſeeketh out the comelieſt, the ſweeteſt, and the richeſt things to reſemble him. This ſhould excite vs, who ſeeke<note place="margin">Whom wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſeeke we to enioy him.</note> things tranſitorie and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, with great care, to giue our temples no reſt, nor our eye-lids no leaue to ſlumber, vntill we haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed our ſelues in this onely begotten, in whom as a common treaſurie and conceptacle all bleſsings ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, from all eternity purpoſed, and in time giuen vs, are repoſed. And on the other ſide, ſuch as haue this rich pearle of the Goſpell ſhould with the Apoſtle, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. in heauineſſe be reioicing;<note place="margin">And hauing him to reioyce in him.</note> in pouertie making others rich; and when they haue nothing, be as thoſe which poſſeſſe all things.</p>
            <p>The fourth<note place="margin">4. In the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of giuing him.</note> and laſt thing is the manner of giuing. This that wee may more fully conceiue, may fitly be conſidered in three degrees.<note place="margin">That was three waies.</note> Firſt, Chriſt was giuen in the moment of incarnation: Secondly, in the whole courſe of his life, to fulfill obedience on our behalfe: Thirdly, hee was giuen to ſuffer death, the accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed death of the Croſſe, that wee might be deliuered. The firſt of theſe is cleare many waies; 1.<note place="margin">Firſt, in his very birth.</note> by ſcripture, 2. by the confeſsions of the antient Churches, 3. by reaſon: and in the fourth place, the contrary hath beene condemned of hereſie. We muſt not conceiue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1709:16"/> Chriſt to come into the world as for himſelfe and his owne buſineſſe,<note place="margin">Our ſaluation being his onely errand, and not his owne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancement.</note> and to take the work of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as a matter by the way: but we are ſo to take him in the moment of his incarnation, as beſtowed on vs by God the Father: as is plainely affirmed, <hi>Eſay</hi> 9.6. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. And in this laſt allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſcripture the Authour plainely ſheweth, as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">And he being incarnate.</note> ſo the cauſe and end for which Chriſt tooke fleſh. Becauſe (ſaith he) the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren were partakers of fleſh and bloud, he alſo tooke part with them, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is, the Diuell. In which place two things are very obſerueable; 1.<note place="margin">1. That he might dy for vs.</note> that Chriſt tooke fleſh, that in this nature which was capable of ſuffring, through death hee might obtaine victory. 2.<note place="margin">Be like to vs.</note> Mark, that the fleſh of Chriſt is made re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectiue to a former type, to wit; the nature of the children, the worke of whoſe redemption was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to him. And this point is to be laid vp againſt ſuch, who holding the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, though man had not fallen, make him the firſt in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, though the laſt in execution. If that Chriſts fleſh and bloud had beene firſt intended, then the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhould haue reference to him as the firſt ſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler; who are now made the patterne of his humane nature, as for whom it was onely vndertaken. And ſo all the Confeſsions, the <hi>Nicen,</hi> that of <hi>Damaſus,</hi> the <hi>Epheſine,</hi> the <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> run perpetually in this ſtile, <hi>Propter nos, nostramque ſalutem, propter nos homines, et ad implendas ſcripturas, deſcendit à Patre, natus ex Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, homo factus eſt;</hi> that is, For vs and our ſaluation, for vs men, &amp; to fulfill the Scriptures, he came downe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1709:16"/> from the Father, was borne of the virgin, and made man: And none conſider Chriſt as coming for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but as giuen to vs in his firſt entrance. And in the hymne of Saint <hi>Ambroſe, Te Deum,</hi> thus much wee ſtill confeſſe, when wee ſay, that Chriſt taking on him the redemption of mankinde, did not abhor the virgins wombe: namely, that his conception &amp; birth was for our auaile. Laſtly, antiquity did oppoſe no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to <hi>Marcion</hi> and the <hi>Manichees,</hi> then this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. For when they obiected, that it beſeemed not the ſuper eminent excellency of the diuine nature, who would not take the nature of angells, to aſſume fleſh conſubſtantiall with ours, who are but duſt and aſhes: and when againe they replyed, that ſeeing the Angels appearing did not vſe in their miniſterie true but ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary bodies; and if true, yet they neuer tooke them into vnity of their perſon; it was vnlikely that the Son of God would euer perſonally vnite our nature vnto him: To theſe I ſay, and ſuch like humane conceits, the ancients oppoſed this ſimple confeſsion, that though Chriſt for himſelfe need not, yet for our ſakes he did not eſchew the womb of the virgin. Thirdly, in reaſon this is conuinced as a truth. For, when incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is a degree of humiliation vnto God, what had the Son of God done, that hee ſhould by putting on the veile of fleſh empty himſelfe of glory, and become of no reputation? And therefore the Authour to the Hebrewes putteth all the decency of Chriſts afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and abiection in this, becauſe many by him were to bee aduanced. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.10. Neither was there any cauſe why he ſhould become God-man before the fall.<note place="margin">There was no cauſe on Chriſt of his incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but for vs, nor no need our before the fall.</note> It is ſaid that elſe he could not be a fit head. I anſwer;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1709:17"/> How was he a head to all the Angels before their fall, and is ſtill to thoſe elect ones that haue kept their firſt eſtate? when yet their nature is not aſſumed. Laſtly, <hi>Cyril</hi> taketh this in his third book of his <hi>Theſaurus,</hi> as a concluſion of Artianiſme, that Chriſt <hi>magis vt ipſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altaretur, nomenque maximum conſequeretur, quam pre noſtra ſalute, homo factus eſſet:</hi> that is, was made man rather that he might be exalted, and obtaine a great name, then for our ſaluation. And afterward asketh why he ſhould be called our Sauiour, if hee did more for himſelfe then for vs. There is ſomewhat, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9. that ſeemeth to make for this, that the end of Chriſts humiliation was that he might be exalted. But the il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue particle, wherefore, there notes not the end nor any cauſe, but the euent and conſequent of his humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; tis taken <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecutiuely, not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, cauſally. It is true indeed, that Chriſt could not recouer glory to vs, but that it muſt bee firſt receiued in him, as who is the head and common conceptacle of all his members:<note place="margin">Chriſts coming for himſelfe obſcureth gods grace.</note> but to holde Chriſt in his coming and humiliation, ſeeking himſelfe, may well bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted erroneous. For it obſcureth that grace which the Apoſtle extolleth, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.9. <hi>You knowe the grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, how that hee beeing rich, for your ſakes became poore, that ye through his pouerty might bee made rich.</hi> What words can more plainely ſhewe that Chriſt of himſelfe needed nothing; but that it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſupply our need, that hee did humble and abaſe himſelfe?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. In his life to obey the law for vs.</note>Secondly, He was giuen in the whole courſe of his life, to fulfill the lawe in our behalfe. Of this is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. <hi>When the fulnes of time came, God ſent his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1709:17"/> Son made of a woman, and made vnder the law.</hi> Where though his ſubiection vnto the penalty of the law bee moſt fitly vnderſtood, yet his other obedience muſt not be excluded. For Chriſt euen in his circumciſion teſtified, that he was ſubiect to the whole obedience of the law, aſwell actiue as paſsiue; as which did not onely declare him to be a true man,<note place="margin">To which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e ful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> fit for the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but made him alſo for our ſakes debtour to the whole law (as <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.3. <hi>that the circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſon was bound to keepe the whole law</hi>) for our ſakes I ſay, not his owne.<note place="margin">Not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For Chriſt by nature was a ſonne ouer his Fathers houſe, and not tied to the ſelfe ſame tenour of obedience, whereunto we are obliged. If it be obiected, that as he was the ſonne, ſo he was a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo, and therefore ſubiect to the law: the anſwer is ready;<note place="margin">Though he w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that a reaſonable creature muſt bee confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the righteouſnes of the law, but not ſubiect to this or that obedience; becauſe that ſuch ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dependeth not on creation, but on the will of the Creator. <hi>Adam</hi> was not ſubiect to that prohibition concerning the eating of the fruit, vntill it pleaſed the law-giuer to impoſe it on him. <hi>Ob.</hi> But Chriſt was in <hi>Adams</hi> loines, with whom the couenant of works was ſtricken; and therefore hee muſt fulfill the lawe for himſelfe. Whereto I ſay; 1. That the couenant was ſtricken with thoſe who were not onely in <hi>Adam,</hi> but were by him alſo: but our Sauiour came not by him through carnall propagation, as do other men, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hee were in him taking his fleſh of the virgin. 2. The hypoſtaticall vnion, whereby his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture did growe into one perſon with the Son of God, did exempt him from this ſubiection: but that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1709:18"/> him for our ſakes to ſubmit himſelfe thereunto;<note place="margin">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t by his own will for vs.</note> whoſe cauſe as hee had vndertaken, ſo was hee to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme our obedience:<note place="margin">He b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>coming our ſurety.</note> which this one reaſon may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhew and confirm. What we ſtand charged with, Chriſt was bound to diſcharge: For hee became our ſurety, whoſe office is to pay all the bonds of the poor debtour for whom hee doth vndertake. But wee are charged,<note place="margin">Who are bound to keepe the law.</note> not onely breaking the law, to vndergoe the curſe; but to doe it alſo vnto life. For thus <hi>Moſes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth the righteouſneſſe of the lawe; Hee that doth theſe things ſhall liue in them. Doe this, and liue. It is excepted; This ſtands in force onely while the couenant of works obtaineth and taketh place; which is now aboliſhed. To which I anſwer; that ſo the law is changed, that it remaineth as a rule of righteouſnes: and this order, that the righteouſnes of the law muſt be fulfilled, ere life bee obtained, in it ſelfe is not alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.<note place="margin">And this order being immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes muſt be fulfilled, ere life be obtained.</note> 
               <hi>Heauen and earth ſhall paſſe away, but one iot or tittle of the law ſhall not paſſe vnaccompliſhed. Mat.</hi> 5.18. This, the phraſe of the ſcriptture teacheth alſo: it ſaith the curſe is taken away, not the law; <hi>Ye are dead to the law. Rom.</hi> 7.4. And, <hi>I am dead to the law. Gal.</hi> 2.19. It doth not ſay, that any particle of the lawe is dead or aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: teaching hereby, that the alteration is in vs who are variable, not in the Lords order which is immuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Wherefore, Do this, and liue, muſt be fulfilled, and ſo it is. But here is the difference, that the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of this righteouſnes which the law preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, in the goſpell is tranſlated to the perſon of a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour.<note place="margin">In the law by our ſelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, in the goſpell by our Mediatour</note> 
               <hi>I come</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.17.) <hi>not to aboliſh, but to fulfill the law and the Prophets.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paul</hi> doubteth not to ſay, that <hi>the righteouſneſſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1709:18"/> of the Law is ſtill fulfilled in vs. Rom.</hi> 8.4. Namely <hi>Euangelicè</hi> and <hi>applicatiuè,</hi> according to the tenour of the Goſpell, &amp; by application; but in Chriſt, <hi>legaliter</hi> and <hi>inhaeſiuè,</hi> according to the Law inhaeſiuely in himſelfe.<note place="margin">3 Cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y in Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſo ſmall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce.</note> Why then (will ſome ſay) doth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſpeake ſo little of this kinde of obedience, and ſo much of his paſsion? There are ſundry cauſes of it. Firſt, becauſe That of his Paſsion was moſt ſenſible and expoſed to the eyes of all. Secondly, becauſe that the Ceremoniall types had in that, their accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment. Thirdly, becauſe his Paſsion hath in it the chiefe actuall obedience. See <hi>Chryſostom</hi> in the ſecond homily on the <hi>Acts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third degree of the giuing of Chriſt,<note place="margin">3. In his death to ſuff r for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth more agreeably with this place, is the giuing of him to be lifted vp vpon the tree, that there in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die hee might beare our ſinnes. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24. For in his lifting vp (which phraſe noteth the manner of his death) hee anſwereth to the type of the brazen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.14. Which as whoſo looked on had cure for the ſtings of the fierie ſerpents; ſo wee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on Chriſt by faith, are cured of the ſting of that old ſerpent, ſinne and death. Of this giuing, <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. He hath giuen his own Sonne for vs all.<note place="margin">Which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the height <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> And the <hi>Epitaſis</hi> and height of Gods loue is made manifeſt in it, that our hearts ſhould burne within vs. Yea, with the Spouſe in the Canticles, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5. we ſhould ſwoone to conſider it. For what vnſpeakeable loue is it that Almightie God a father ſo glorious, and full of Maieſtie, ſhould giue his onely Sonne, a ſonne like and equall to himſelfe, for his enemies, to be made vnder the Law,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1709:19"/> yea, the curſe of the Law, and to be deliuered vp to the powers of darkneſſe. This doctrine hath foure vſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Vſes.</hi> 1. To make vs mourne for our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nnes,</note>Firſt, it ſerueth to ſhew vs how horrible ſinne is, to engender in vs godly griefe, and to make vs ſtudiouſly auoide it. Such Epicuriſme is in vs, that wee count ſinne a light hurt, which any thing will ſalue. But whoſo duely weigheth this, that ſinne ere it could bee done away and ſatisfied, hath made the Lord of glory to empty himſelfe of his Maieſtie, the Son of God to walke as a ſeruant, God himſelfe to ſhed his bloud; this will make his heart to melt &amp; bleed within him for his ſinnes, and to water his cheekes with teares, no leſſe aboundantly, then he hath before laughed merrily and blithely. <hi>I will poure</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>Zachary</hi> 12.10.) <hi>vpon the houſe</hi> Dauid, <hi>and vpon the inhabitants of Ieruſalem the ſpirit of grace and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion, and they ſhall looke vpon mee whom they haue pearced, and they ſhall lament for him as one mourneth for his onely ſonne, and be ſorry for him, as one is ſorry for his firſt borne, &amp;c.</hi> If once the Lord make vs turne our eyes to Chriſt, and to regard what he hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for our ſinnes, nothing will more then that hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vs with godly ſorrow, and bruiſe our hearts for them. For what ſorrow can we thinke deepe enough, what teares ſufficient, for our ſinnes which haue pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the Sonne of God vvith extreame ſorrowes, and put him to moſt baſe, vile and painefull ſufferings! And this grace alſo will curbe a man moſt effectually from breaking forth into euill.<note place="margin">and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o curbe vs from ſinne.</note> As <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. <hi>The grace of God which bringeth ſaluation vnto all men hath appeared, and teacheth vs that wee ſhould deny vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1709:19"/> and worldly luſts.</hi> What is this grace of God? but that fauour and loue vvhich God hath ſhewed vs in the ſufferings of Chriſt; then the vvhich there is no better maſter to teach vs, and to preſſe vpon vs this leſſon of vſing all endeauour to ſhunne ſinne. For therein as in a cleere glaſſe may we contemplate and behold what Chriſt hath endured to free vs from it: what fearefull torments it deſerueth: how odious and hatefull it is to God, which he would ſo ſeuerely puniſh in his owne Sonne: And laſtly, into vvhat hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible miſery, it will eternally plunge vs, if we doe not ſhake it off, and abſtaine therefrom.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. To comfort in temptation.</note>Secondly, it is comfortable in temptation. For when Sathan ſhall trouble our mindes, and charge vs with our ſinnes and vvant of righteouſneſſe, there is nothing in the world that can quiet our mindes, and ſtop his mouth but this, that Chriſts righteouſneſſe and ſatisfaction is ours;<note place="margin">Shewing Chriſt to be ours.</note> and that by his death we are acquitted from our ſinnes, and by his righteouſneſſe made righteous before God. But how is Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and ſatisfaction made ours? Euen by the gift and donation of God. For, as wee haue heard,<note place="margin">By Gods gift.</note> God hath giuen vs his Sonne: and if Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe be giuen vs, doubtleſſe vvith Chriſt wee haue all the merits of his obedience conferred on vs by the ſame gift. And what better right and title can we haue to him and his righteouſneſſe then this, that God who is the ſole owner &amp; poſſeſſour of him, hath beſtowed him on vs?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. To make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> truſt to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or all other good things Rom. 8 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Thirdly, it is a ground of hope in all our vvants, that God vvill ſupply vnto vs all things good and needfull. For hath God giuen vs Chriſt his Sonne?
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1709:20"/> How ſhall hee not with him giue vs all things alſo? No man, vvhoſe kindneſſe and loue to vs hath beene ſo great as to beſtow on vs the beſt and deareſt thing he hath, vvill hold backe any thing that ſhould make that gift ſure and behoouefull to vs, or ſee vs in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe for want of ſmaller matters. Loe: God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs his Sonne, the moſt excellent, deere and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious thing he had. And can wee thinke that his loue is ſo cold, as that hee vvill ſticke to beſtow vpon vs earthly things, that are toyes and trifles to this great gift, if he ſee them fit for vs? or that he will not giue vs faith and other graces, whereby this gift ſhould be made certaine, and of vſe vnto vs?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e vs of the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s loue her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</note>Fourthly, it doth aſſure vs of Gods loue for the time to come. If when we were enemies, vvee were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne, much more being reconciled, ſhall wee bee ſaued by his life. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10. If a man out of loue haue ſought the friendſhip of his enemie, and vſed meanes to be reconciled to him, is it not likely that he will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in this loue, and take all waies to maintaine it vnto the end? But howſoeuer it fall out with man who is variable; moſt ſure it is, that GOD ſince his loue was ſo wonderfull toward vs when wee were enemies, that hee gaue his Sonne for vs, to reconcile vs to him, will now much more freely exerciſe his loue toward vs, and firmely abide in his good vvill vnto vs, that enmitie being vndone and diſſolued.</p>
            <p>Now the end followeth in theſe three things. Firſt, the meanes, <hi>whoſoeuer beleeueth on him.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the ſtate from whence wee are deliuered, <hi>ſhall not periſh:</hi> Thirdly, the condition to which wee are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1709:20"/> 
               <hi>but ſhall haue euerlaſting life.</hi> In the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> the meanes, I conſider theſe three things. Firſt, that the beleeuer hath a benefit aboue others. Secondly, the vniuerſalitie of this benefit, <hi>whoſoeuer beleeueth.</hi> Thirdly, the obiect which our faith muſt reſt vpon; <hi>beleeue on him.</hi> Theſe remaine to bee handled, and then wee will proceede to the ſtate from vvhence we are deliuered, and condition whereto we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued. Firſt, then Chriſt maketh this the end of Gods giuing him, that euery one beleeuing ſhould not periſh, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Doct. 5. All of wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſort ſoeuer, belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing are ſaued.</note>The point which wee are heere to obſerue, is, that without regard of any outward circumſtance, as well one as other, is by faith iuſtified, and ſhall bee ſaued: All ſorts of people that beleeue, are made thereby heires of Saluation. Which is plaine by teſtimony of the Scripture, and euident by reaſon: <hi>The grace of God hath appeared, and doth bring ſaluation vnto all mon. Tit.</hi> 2.11. So <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.22, 23. <hi>The righteouſneſse of God is now made manifeſt by the faith of Ieſus Christ, vnto all, and vpon all that beleeue. For there is no difference:</hi> There is in this caſe, no Nation before Nation; no preheminence of any ſexe, ſort, kinde or degree aboue other: but as well the Gentile, as the Iew; the poore, as the rich; vnlearned, as learned, euery one that belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth is an heire of life, and child of God. For thus is it expounded, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16. <hi>The Goſpell is the power of God vnto ſaluation to euery one that beleeueth; to the Iew first, and alſo to the Grecian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſons. Reaſon 1.</note>Now the firſt reaſon of this vniuerſalitie in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of ſaluation, <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſet downe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.29. For hauing laid downe this generall propoſition, that a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1709:21"/> man, euen euery one is iuſtified by faith; leſt the Iew (as he was apt to doe) ſhould ſtomacke and diſdaine this equality and fellowſhip of the Gentile in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of ſaluation, doth adde a reaſon for it. What (ſaith he) is God the God of the Iew onely, and not of the Gentiles alſo? Yea, of the Gentiles alſo. If then you aske why the world beleeuing doth inherit the bleſsing: we anſwere, euen becauſe God hath pleaſed to be the God of all without difference; of Gentile as well as Iew, of one as well as other. So againe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.11, 12. <hi>Whoſoeuer beleeueth on him ſhall not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</hi> What? Gentile as well as Iew? Yea ſurely. <hi>For there is no difference betweene them: and hee that is Lord ouer all, is rich vnto all that call on him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 2.</note>A ſecond reaſon is opened, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.32. from the purpoſe of God in ſhutting the Gentiles vp in vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. And what was that? Not that they ſhould bee vtterly &amp; finally reiected, but that he might at length ſhew mercy on them; his iuſtice miniſtring and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king way vnto his mercy: euen as now he dealeth with the Iewes whom hee hath caſt off for a ſeaſon, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue them againe with the greater mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 3.</note>Thirdly, it is neceſſarie that it ſhould be ſo, that the Lord might cleere and manifeſt his equitie, as moſt free from acceptation of perſons; that it might bee ſeene that neither Iew found acceptance with him as a Iew; nor the Gentile was the leſſe accepted vvith him as a Gentile. Wherefore <hi>Peter</hi> when he ſaw in a manner the firſt fruits of the Gentiles, ſaith; <hi>Act.</hi> 10.34, 35. <hi>Of a trueth I perceiue that God is no accepter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: But in euery Nation he that feareth him and worketh righteouſneſſe is accepted with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:1709:21"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 4.</note>Fourthly, this was prefigured in <hi>Abraham; Rom.</hi> 4.10, 11. who by faith obtained the account of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, euen when hee was vncircumciſed, as well as after circumciſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 5.</note>Laſtly, it was forepropheſied, that in the ſeed of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> all the Nations of the earth ſhould be bleſſed: <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.18. that is, haue the bleſsing of righteouſnes, and life through faith.</p>
            <p>But now when was this ſpecially accompliſhed,<note place="margin">Saluation was impa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts of people moſt ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiful y vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pell.</note> that the world through faith did receiue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? euen in the day of ſaluation, in the acceptable yeere which was forepropheſied of, and which the Apoſtle applyeth to the times of the Goſpell: 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. and beganne from the Aſcenſion of Chriſt to receiue generall execution. <hi>Act</hi> 13.46, 47. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this vniuerſalitie of beleeuers is heere made to follow the lifting vp, and giuing of Chriſt, as procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thereby: as alſo he ſpeaketh elſewhere. <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.32. when I am lifted vp, I will draw all men vnto me. In Chriſt then is the world reconciled; in his death the wall of partition broken downe, and both Iew and Gentile created into one new man. The Iewes onely were, before, the people of God. And no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is it that ſauing knowledge was ſo ſtraitly confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: For they had Chriſt but in the ſhaddow onely; and the light which did ſhine to them was as the light of a Candle, and might eaſily bee bounded in little compaſſe: but when the Sunne of righteouſneſſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, it was impoſsible but that the beames of it ſhould be ſpread through the face of the earth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Vſes.</hi> 1. An helpe to explicate ſome Scriptures ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of all.</note>Firſt, this helpeth for the vnderſtanding of many Scriptures: as of that 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.2. that Chriſt is a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1709:22"/> for the ſinnes of the whole world; and <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. that hee taſted death for all men; with the like. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. What is in theſe Scriptures the world? What all men? Muſt wee vnderſtand thereby, as ſome would haue it, the whole body of mankinde, and euery particular perſon in the world? There is no ſuch thing. But theſe vniuerſals muſt be vnderſtood, as in this place, All that beleeue. So there is a threefold vniuerſalitie:<note place="margin">A threefo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d vniue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſilitie.</note> firſt of all in generall, both good and euill, we muſt all appeare before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeate of Chriſt, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. Secondly, of all euill and vnbeleeuing perſons, expreſſed by the world, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.9. Thirdly, of all beleeuing ones, as in the former Scriptures; a ſpeciall vniuerſalitie, as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> doth call it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. A lig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to ſhew vs our happineſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles before Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt.</note>Secondly, this teacheth vs our happineſſe aboue the Gentiles of former times, who foure thouſand yeeres almoſt were no people, without God, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtranged from the life of God: but wee now belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing are become conſederates with God. We ſee his ſaluation; as they who liue in the acceptable time which hee ordained. When the holy men of God looked vnto this time, with what ioy were they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed? As it is ſaid of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he ſaw this day of Chriſt, and reioiced thereat. <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.56. And if the contemplation of it before hand made them to reioyce; How much more ſhould wee reioyce in this grace of God, and in this day of ſaluation, vnto whom it is riſen, and who enioy the comfortable and bleſſed preſence of it?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. An exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion to imbrace the preſent grace offred vs.</note>Thirdly, it is a ground of exhortation to vs, that wee put not the grace of God from vs. Euery one
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1709:22"/> that beleeueth ſhall be ſaued. That is, no condition, no not of the greateſt excepted, of whom this is not required, To beleeue. Look to me all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee Nations of the earth, and be you ſaued.</p>
            <p>Be men what they will be, neuer ſo rich, noble and great, they muſt looke and goe to Chriſt if they will haue ſaluation. What happineſſe is this then, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt is come vnto vs, and this grace is offered vs? It is iuſt with God that wee periſh, if on any worldly confidence we neglect this ſaluation, and do not with both armes embrace and lay hold of it, being thus brought vnto vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 6. The onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of our faith as it iuſtifies vs, is Chriſt.</note>Now it followeth, euery one beleeuing on him.</p>
            <p>This doth teach what is the obiect of our faith: that is Ieſus Chriſt, whom onely faith doth looke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to and reſpect, as it doth make vs righteous in the ſight of God: which other Scriptures plentifully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme. To as many as receiued him hee gaue this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge, to bee the ſonnes of God, euen to them that beleeue in his name. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. A worthy honour to be made the Sonne of God, which faith onely can aduance vs to; and that onely as it doth beleeue in Chriſt, and receiue him. And ſo <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30, 31. What ſaith the Iayler muſt I doe to bee ſaued? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, doth <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> anſwere him. But on whom? on the Lord Ieſus: And <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. that they may receiue forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that are ſanctified through faith in mee. It is therefore called the faith of Chriſt, becauſe Chriſt is he whom faith doth apprehend to righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and life; according to that in the twenty ſixt Verſe of this Chapter; <hi>Hee that beleeueth on the Sonne
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1709:23"/> of God hath life.</hi> And righteouſneſſe is euery vvhere tied vnto faith, euen to faith in Chriſt, whom onely it doth and can looke vnto as it iuſtifieth vs. It is true, that a iuſtifying faith may worke a miracle, may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue an hiſtorie: but it doth not iuſtifie vs, as it is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied this way; neither in theſe things doth it onely eye Ieſus Chriſt. For there are thoſe who may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the hiſtory of the goſpell, yea, and worke mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles alſo, who were neuer iuſtified: as wee may reade, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.22.23. But this matter will bee better cleared, if we conſider what it is to beleeue on Chriſt. The papiſts ſay, it is to giue credit to the doctrine touching Chriſt his perſon, offices, paſsion and merits: we ſay, it is confidence of mercy in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Which faith is a confidence of mercy in Chriſt</note> touching pardon of ſinne, and life. In handling of this point I will firſt cleare the truth, then anſwer what may bee obiected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. This then, that faith is an affiance of mercy, is proued by the nature of the phraſe; ſecondly, by the interpretation of ſcripture; thirdly, by reaſons.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">As is manifeſt by the phraſe.</note>The phraſe, to beleeue on Chriſt, notes confidence &amp; aſſurance: as may eaſily be conuinced. For ſo theſe three phraſes, <hi>Credere de Christo, credere Chriſto, et cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere in Chriſtum</hi> (To beleeue concerning Chriſt, to beleeue Chriſt, and to beleeue on Chriſt) muſt bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, that the former two include a bare know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and aſſent, and may be where there is no iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but the laſt containeth confidence in it, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doth iuſtifie. This phraſe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to theſe Hebrew phraſes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>batach,</hi> in conſtruction with <hi>beth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For theſe referred to God are all one,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſal. 18.22.</note> vſed ſometime in way of <hi>exegeſis</hi> and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition the one to the other. That theſe anſwer to this
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1709:23"/> greek phraſe, is apparant both by comparing the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riacke, and by the tranſlation of the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> who ſo tranſlate it; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, out of the 28. of <hi>Eſay,</hi> verſe 16. as <hi>Paul</hi> citeth it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.11. Looke now how the Scripure expoundeth theſe phraſes.<note place="margin">2. By the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> In the 50. of <hi>Eſay</hi> 10. you haue one expounded. <hi>Truſt in the Lord,</hi> the meaning whereof is giuen vs in the next words, <hi>and reſt vpon him.</hi> So <hi>Eſay</hi> 31.1. the ſame phraſe to truſt, is expounded by ſtaying, euen as a man would ſtay himſelfe on a ſtaffe, wherewith he is vnderprop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: So alſo <hi>Ier.</hi> 17.5. <hi>To trust in man, is to make man his arme, letting the hart go back from God.</hi> In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.7. <hi>To truſt on the Lord, is to place our ſtrength in the Lord.</hi> And <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.5. <hi>To truſt in him, is for a man to roule him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his actions on him.</hi> If to beleeue on God, were to holde dogmatically this or that reuealed of him, then this beleefe were common to other things with him, and wee might as well beleeue in creatures as in God. For what doth let, but that we may without ſin holde and aſſent to thoſe dogmaticall truthes, which are taught concerning them. Adde to theſe things the iudgement of <hi>Augustine</hi> on the 77. <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eſt crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re in Deum. cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere ad benè coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum bona o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perant. Deo. Aug. in pſal. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>This</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is to beleeue in God; By beleeuing to cleaue vnto him.</hi> And more largely on <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7. <hi>tract.</hi> 29.<note n="b" place="margin">Si creditis in eum creditis ei non autem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> qui credit ei, credit in eum, &amp;c. De Apoſtolis poſſumus dicere, credimus Paulo, ſed non credimus in Paulum; credimus Petro, ſed non credimus in Petrum, &amp;c. Quid eſt ergo credere in eum? credendo amare credendo dilige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, credendo in eum ire, &amp; eius membris incorporari. Auguſtine in Iohannem: cap. <hi>7.</hi> tract <hi>29.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>If ye beleeue in God, ye alſo beleeue God; but not forthwith doth he beleeue in God, who beleeueth God. Againe we may ſay, we beleeue</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Peter, <hi>but not wee beleeue in</hi> Paul <hi>and</hi> Peter. <hi>What is therefore to beleeue in him? it is by beleeuing to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect him, by beleeuing to loue him, by beleeuing to goe into
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1709:24"/> him, and to bee incorporated into his members.</hi> In which ſenſe &amp; words alſo <hi>Lumbard:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Credere in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eſt credendo amare, credendo in eum ire, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo ei adhaere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, et eius mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris incorporari Lomb lib. <hi>3.</hi> diſtinct. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> doth expound the ſame phraſe, <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>dist.</hi> 23.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is manifeſt by the ſcripture, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. and <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. that beleeuing on Chriſt is the receiuing of him. And what is this receiuing? Not only a compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of the vnderſtanding, but an imbracing of the hart and affections; laying holde on him, as we would on any thing with our hand which is reached vnto vs. And <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.35. to goe or come to Chriſt, is made all one with beleeuing on Chriſt: which going no doubt is rather a ſpirituall motion of the hart and affections toward Chriſt, to enioy him and cleaue vnto him, then a contemplation of the minde contented to ſee &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. By reaſons.</note>In the third place wee muſt cleare this matter by reaſon, that to beleeue on Chriſt is to truſt vpon him, and that for the grace of remiſsion of ſinnes, and life euerlaſting. For the papiſts ſay, that when we conſtrue to beleeue in Chriſt, to bee, to beleeue the pardon of our ſinnes in and for Chriſt, that this is a gloſſe of our owne deuiſing. Wherefore to ſhew it, let this bee the firſt reaſon; So faith doth receiue and reſt on Chriſt, as Chriſt is ſet forth to the beleeuer. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 1.</note>But Chriſt is ſet forth vnto vs as our redeemer from ſinne and death; <hi>ergo</hi> faith ſtaieth on Chriſt as our redeemer from ſin and death. For, this wee are alwaies to haue in minde, that Chriſt is the obiect of our faith,<note place="margin">Not a naked Chriſt is the obiect of our faith, but Chriſt clothed with his benefits.</note> not abſtractly and nakedly conſidered, but Chriſt with his benefits, Chriſt lifted vp as the brazen ſerpent, Chriſt ſet forth as a ſacrifice propitiatory for our ſinnes. And thus to receiue Chriſt and beleeue on him, is to beleeue &amp;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1709:24"/> receiue in him ranſome from ſin and death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 2.</note>Secondly, I proue this from the diſpoſition of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beleeuer. That which pricketh and ſpurreth the ſoule to Chriſt; that the ſoule firſt of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eacheth at, and receiueth in Chriſt. But ſinne and death maketh the ſoule goe forth to Chriſt; <hi>Ergo,</hi> it firſt layeth hold on pardon of ſinne, and deliuerance from death. Theſe things are euident truths, in the experience of euery humbled and beleeuing ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 3.</note>Thirdly, it may bee proued by the order of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that a iuſtifying faith is to ſtay on Chriſt for the pardon of ſinne, or to beleeue in him forgiueneſſe of ſinne.</p>
            <p>The beleeuer that hath got his ſinnes couered, he hath beleeued the pardon of them. But euery beleeuer whom God iuſtifyeth, hath firſt got his ſins couered; <hi>Ergo,</hi> he hath before iuſtification, beleeued their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. It may ſeeme ſtrange, that I ſay, that the ſinnes of the beleeuer are couered before his iuſtification: but in nature thus it muſt bee conſidered. For the Lord cannot pronounce vs as iuſt, till ſome way hee ſee vs innocent. To abſolue the guiltie is abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with him. The order that is obſerued in our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication<note place="margin">The order of our iuſtificat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> will cleere the matter. Firſt, there is a ſight of our miſery; to which we are brought by the Law: Secondly, there is by the Goſpell an holding forth of Chriſt, as our Redemption from ſinne and death: Thirdly, there is a working of faith in the heart to reſt on Chriſt, as the ranſome from ſinne, and death. Now when a man is come hither, he is truely and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally iuſt. For he hath hold of the ranſome from all his ſinne. Then in the fourth place followeth the Lords
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1709:25"/> voice, iuſtifying this party, thus in Chriſt made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 4.</note>Fourthly, it may be proued by the effects of faith: For that faith which iuſtifyeth before God, which ſanctifyeth, which bringeth Chriſt to dwell in our hearts, which breedeth peace, yea giueth entrance vnto God with confidence, and boldneſſe; that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the truſt of mercy, and in knowledge onely. But all theſe are made effects of beleeuing on Chriſt. The firſt part of the reaſon is euident: For if faith be onely the crediting of things to be beleeued, then theſe eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts belong not vnto faith. For wicked men in their kinde, and the Diuels in their kinde, may haue ſuch a perſwaſion.</p>
            <p>Thus hauing proued ſufficiently, that to beleeue on Chriſt, is to haue confidence of mercy, touching remiſsion of ſinne; I will now ſhew what may bee obiected.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Obiections anſwered. Scriptures that ſeeme to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme faith to be onely a right perſwaſion of Chriſts perſon and offices.</note>The arguments are either drawne from Scripture or Reaſon. The firſt ranke proueth that it is true faith to think aright of Chriſts perſon &amp; office. The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures may be recalled to theſe three heads: <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Thou art the Chriſt, the Son of the liuing God. Iohn</hi> 1.49. <hi>Rabbi,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nathanael, thou art the Sonne of God, thou art the King of Iſrael. Iohn</hi> 11.26, 27. <hi>He that beleeueth in mee</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour vnto <hi>Martha) ſhall not dye.</hi> Beleeueſt thou this? <hi>Yea Lord</hi> (ſaith ſhee) <hi>I beleeue that thou art the Chriſt, the Sonne of God that ſhould come into the world.</hi> So <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.31. <hi>Theſe things are written that yee might beleeue that Ieſus is the Chriſt, the Sonne of God, &amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. and 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.1. From all theſe Scriptures it may thus be concluded.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:1709:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> To bee perſwaded aright touching Chriſts perſon and office, is no particular aſſurance of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: But rightly to hold this, is iuſtifying faith: <hi>Ergo,</hi> iuſtifying faith is no particular affiance, but onely to hold truely the doctrine of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But it is falſe, that theſe examples men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion no more but the holding of the doctrine in truth. For they all include an affiance of mercy,<note place="margin">Which yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude in affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of mercy in him.</note> which may be thus proued. Firſt, it is a generall rule, that words of knowledge include in the partie the affections alſo: much more, words of beliefe. Secondly, to ſee the cleere trueth of all theſe examples, wee muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the diſpoſition of Gods people touching the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah. As therefore they looked for the Meſsiah, ſo according to the prophecies they promiſed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in and by the Meſsiah all good. The woman of Samaria, <hi>Iohn</hi> 4. could ſay, when the Meſsiah com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, he will teach vs all things. And therefore <hi>Math.</hi> 11.3. the Diſciples of <hi>Iohn</hi> aske Chriſt, <hi>Art thou hee that ſhould come, or ſhall wee looke for another.</hi> Where wee may ſee, that there was not a knowledge onely of Chriſt to come, but an expectation and an hope placed in him, as in whom all good promiſes ſhould bee accompliſhed vnto them. So that if we conſider the diſpoſition of this people, whoſe hopes did hang on the Meſsiah, wee may plainely vnderſtand how that to beleeue the Meſsias, is not onely to know and giue credence; but to haue an affiance in him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, wee muſt conſider theſe examples by that of <hi>Thomas, Iohn</hi> 20.28. who as he confeſſed Chriſt and God, ſo was it with tearmes of affiance, ſaying, Thou art my Lord and my God. Fourthly, this may
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1709:26"/> bee gathered by <hi>Marthaes</hi> words: <hi>Iohn</hi> 11.26, 27. For when Chriſt asked her, Doeſt thou beleeue this, that whoſo beleeueth on me ſhall not die euerlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; She doth anſwere, <hi>Yea Lord: I beleeue that thou art the Chriſt:</hi> that is, Since I beleeue this that thou art the Meſsiah, I cannot doubt but that thoſe that cleaue to thee ſhall haue euerlaſting life; teaching that theſe confeſsions imply an affiance and truſt of all good through him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ranke of places proue, that to beleeue the power of God is iuſtifying faith.<note place="margin">Scriptures af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming faith to be a beliefe of Gods power.</note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.28. &amp;c. Chriſt required no more of the blinde man, then to beleeue that hee was able to heale him. And <hi>Luke</hi> the ſeuenth, that faith of the Centurion which Chriſt commended to be greater then hee had found any in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſeemeth to bee no more then a perſwaſion of Chriſts power to reſtore his ſicke ſeruant: <hi>Say the word and my ſeruant ſhall be whole. verſe</hi> 7. So <hi>Marke</hi> 1.4. The Leper ſeemeth to doubt of Chriſts will, but was well perſwaded of his power. <hi>If thou wilt thou canſt make me cleane.</hi> And how is <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſet out vnto vs? then by this, that hee was fully aſſured that he which had promiſt was alſo able to doe it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.21. Hence it is thus argued. That faith which Chriſt requireth, and confirmeth by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, that is a iuſtifying faith. But to bee perſwaded touching the power of God, is that faith which hee requireth, and hath ſo confirmed, <hi>Ergo</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>I anſwere to the firſt part of this reaſon; that it is falſe. For the faith which Chriſt requireth to iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, is ſuch a faith as doth acquite vs from our ſinnes, and procure vs righteouſneſſe: but ſuch a faith
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1709:26"/> is not heere required, but onely a faith ſeruing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a temporall bleſsing:<note place="margin">Which ſpeake not of iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith, but of a faith auailing to temporall bleſsing.</note> to which faith it ſuffices to bee perſwaded of Gods generall goodneſſe and power, as hee is a Creatour. The which faith ſince it doth giue, vnto God, the glory of power aboue all his creatures, it pleaſeth him to reward with temporall benefits, as a thing good in it ſelfe, though it doe not iuſtifie vs in his ſight.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Abrahams</hi> example muſt bee further examined and explaned, from the which they goe about to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the ſame thus. <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith,</note> was a iuſtifying faith. But his faith was not a perſwaſion of mercy.</p>
            <p>To confirme which, they make two maine excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at this example. Firſt, that it was of a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall promiſe; and <hi>ergo,</hi> the obiect of it was not forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſins in Chriſt. Secondly, that it was of Gods power, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.21. and not of any ſpeciall grace and fauour.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, this promiſe was as well ſpirituall,<note place="margin">was of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall bleſsing.</note> as temporall. It was as you may ſee, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.5.18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of a ſeed which God would raiſe vp out of him, and of <hi>Canaan</hi> which ſhould bee giuen to his ſeede; and in that ſeede, the bleſſed ſeede Ieſus Chriſt:<note place="margin">In Ieſus Chriſt</note> and vnder <hi>Canaan</hi> as a type, heauen was figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and promiſed. Now the obiect of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, ſo farre as it did iuſtifie him, was that bleſſed ſeede which is Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 16. For it was rather the ſight of Chriſt which hee had by faith, then the perſwaſion of a ſonne to bee borne to him, and <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> to be giuen his ſeede, that made him to reioyce: as <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.56. Abraham <hi>reioiced to ſee my day, and hee ſaw it and was glad.</hi> For the ſecond, when they ſay it was a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1709:27"/> perſwaſion of the power of God, and not of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, they are mightily ouerſhot. For the text ſaith firſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 20. that he did not doubt of the promiſe of God. Now the promiſe alwaies implyeth Gods good will,<note place="margin">Looked firſt to Gods good will in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</note> and grace. The promiſe runnes not, I can giue thee a ſeede, <hi>Abraham,</hi> and this <hi>Canaan</hi> to be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by thy ſeede; but, I will do thus and thus. How then doth the Apoſtle ſet out <hi>Abrahams</hi> full beliefe in this, that hee was aſſured that he who had promiſed was able alſo to doe it? I anſwere: Not becauſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> ſaith did iuſtifie him, as it did beleeue the power of God; but becauſe his iuſtifying faith which was fixed on the promiſe, did ſuſtaine it ſelfe<note place="margin">Next, to Gods power, to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine himſelfe in temptation.</note> by this conſideration of Gods power, in the time of triall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the promiſe and execution. For vſually the Lord puts a time of delay betweene theſe; vvherein faith is exerciſed. Thus it was with <hi>Abraham,</hi> he had a promiſe touching a ſeed; the execution is deferred. Hereupon his faith is aſſailed thus. Thy body is dead <hi>Abraham,</hi> thy wife hopeleſſe that way. Theſe things foiled <hi>Sarah.</hi> Now, when <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith on the promiſe is likewiſe ſet vpon, hee holds faſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and againſt theſe arguments of vnbeliefe, faith oppoſeth the all-ſufficient power of God, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaineth it ſelfe with this conſideration; God is able.</p>
            <p>A third ranke of places tendeth to ſhew, that to beleeue Chriſt dead and riſen<note place="margin">Scriptures put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting faith in a beliefe of Chriſts death &amp; reſurrection.</note> is true faith: As <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.9. <hi>If thou ſhalt confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Ieſus, and ſhalt beleeue in thine heart that God raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaued.</hi> And 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.3, 4. &amp;c. it is made the ſumme of the Goſpell, To beleeue the death and reſurrection of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:1709:27"/>
            <p>Hence thus they reaſon; To giue credit that Chriſt is dead and riſen, is a iuſtifying faith: but this is no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of mercy. <hi>Ergo.</hi> I anſwer; The Apoſtles muſt interpret and conſtrue themſelues. To beleeue Chriſt dead and riſen, as they taught him, is true beleefe, but they teach theſe things ſtill with application;<note place="margin">But theſe are to be vnderſtood with applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> as, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.25. <hi>He was deliuered to death for our ſinnes and is riſen againe for our iustification.</hi> And <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34. <hi>Who ſhall condemne? it is Christ which is dead, yea, or rather which is riſen againe; for vs:</hi> for that is to be vnderſtood in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery member of this ſentence, which is added onely in the laſt, that <hi>he maketh requeſt for vs.</hi> So alſo ſay the Apoſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31. <hi>that God had raiſed vp Christ to be a Prince and Sauiour, to giue repentance to Iſrael, &amp; forgiueneſſe of ſinnes.</hi> Now thus to beleeue the death &amp; reſurrection of Chriſt, as thereby to look for forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes, is not bare knowledge, but true affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and aſſurance.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the ſcriptures from the which they would proue this generall faith to be true faith. Now follow the reaſons<note place="margin">Aduerſe reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s anſwered.</note> by which they goe about to ſhewe, that there is not any particular aſſurance of mercie in faith. Firſt then, thus they diſpute; There is no faith where there is no word: but there is no word that ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to any of vs, Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee. <hi>Anſ.</hi> We haue a particular word infolded and wrapped vp in the generall promiſe,<note place="margin">How we haue a particular word for the pardon of our ſinnes in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly</note> as it hath a commandement annexed thereto, for euery one to apply it to himſelfe. If a King ſhall by proclamation exhort his ſubiects, that are riſen in armes againſt him, to lay downe their armes, and ſubmit themſelues vnto him, and withall promiſe that whoſoeuer ſhall ſo doe, ſhall haue his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1709:28"/> is it not as good and firme to euery one that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in accordingly, as if the King had by name ſaid to him; Thou and thou ſhalt haue thy pardon? Now doth not God promiſe pardon &amp; mercy to euery one that beleeueth in the name of Chriſt? and doth he not command euery one to beleeue in Chriſt, and to take this promiſe as made to him in particular? What then is this? but euen as much, as if he did ſay to euery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer by name; Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they obiect, Iuſtifying faith goeth before iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, but the beleefe, that our ſinnes are pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, muſt follow the pardon of them: which they thus proue; The beleefe of the pardon of our ſinnes doth follow our iuſtification, or elſe wee beleeue our ſinnes pardoned when they are not;<note place="margin">Faith and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſin go together.</note> but this were a falſe and fooliſh faith: <hi>Ergo, &amp;c. Anſ.</hi> Neither of theſe is true; For neither doth the beleefe of the pardon of our ſins follow our iuſtification, nor yet doe wee beleeue our ſinnes forgiuen before they bee forgiuen. For God hath thus appointed, that whenſoeuer a ſinner belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and repenteth, his iniquity ſhall then be done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. They goe together. But it will bee asked, How faith can beleeue the pardon of ſinne before the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is really made? we cannot ſee a thing before it be, and ſomething is preſented to vs that is viſible. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Faith requireth one kinde of obiect, ſenſe another: the obiect of ſenſe muſt bee actually exiſting in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of things: but it ſufficeth, that the obiect of faith be in the word of promiſe. Now the pardon of ſinne<note place="margin">Pardon of ſin hath its being in the word of promiſe before we enioy it.</note> hath its being euen before it be beleeued; in regard of Gods decree, then alſo of Chriſts merit and purchaſe, and laſtly, in the word of promiſe, which doth aſſure
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1709:28"/> thee, that vpon thy beleeuing, thy ſinnes are pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Now, faith taketh this pardon preſented to it in the word of promiſe, and trauailing with it bringeth forth the actuall remiſsion of our ſinne, which vpon our faith wee receiue from God. Againe they ſay, if this be iuſtifying faith, to haue truſt and aſſurance that our ſinnes are pardoned, then we cannot ſay as we are taught to pray; Forgiue vs our ſinnes. <hi>Anſ.</hi> That doth not follow: for as in other graces, ſo in faith wee muſt grow, and go from faith to faith, more &amp; more ſtrongly to beleeue the pardon of our ſinnes,<note place="margin">How wee doe pray for the daily pardon of our ſinnes.</note> which already in part wee beleeue: this is it then which vvee craue in that petition, (which we may well do, yea, &amp; ought to do) that for our daily treſpaſſes which wee fall vnto, we may by faith apprehend and obtaine the pardon of them; and for our former treſpaſſes, that the pardon of them may be made good to vs, and by a greater meaſure of faith more firmely apprehended and confirmed to our ſoules. Laſtly, they obiect; Faith is the cauſe of confidence, <hi>ergo</hi> not confidence it ſelfe. <hi>Anſ.</hi> It doth not follow; but rather the contrarie: it breedeth confidence, <hi>ergo</hi> it hath it: for nothing can make another thing hot which hath not heat in it ſelfe: nor could faith ingender confidence in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuer, if in its owne nature it did not containe the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 7. Faith doth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie vs not of it ſelfe, but for Chriſt whom it apprehendeth.</note>
               <hi>That we beleeuing on him)</hi> Before we come to the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of this point, wee may heere fitly obſerue another point that hath much affinity with the former: that is, Whence it is, that faith ſaueth and iuſtifieth vs: it is not for its owne worth, but for Chriſt on whom it reſteth. <hi>GOD gaue his onely begotten Sonne</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1709:29"/> Chriſt) <hi>that we beleeuing on him might haue life,</hi> teaching vs, that for this obiect (that is, Ieſus Chriſt the onely begotten of God) to whom it is referred, whom it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth, wee are iuſtified and ſaued. Wee are to know then, that when we ſay we are iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied by faith, it is all one with this, that wee are iuſtified through Chriſt apprehended by faith. The Papiſts ſay indeed, that this is a gloſſe of our owne making. Wherefore we will a little further cleare and confirme the poynt. Firſt then, the phraſe of Scripture (if we well mark it) will teach vs thus much; that it is not the worthineſs of faith for which we are iuſtified: for wee read, that of faith, and by faith, and through faith wee are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; as <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.1. but we neuer read, for faith we are iuſtified, as if it were aſcribed to the worth of faith. But not to ſtand on this, the equivalence of the former phraſes is the expreſſe word of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.<note place="margin">To be iuſtified by faith, and by Chriſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by faith, is all one.</note> In the third chapter of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and elſewhere, oft we meet with this phraſe, <hi>Wee are iustified by faith:</hi> now in the fift chapter of the ſaid E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle it is ſaid, verſe the 17. that <hi>we ſhall raigne in life through Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> and verſe 19. <hi>that by his obedience we ſhall be made righteous.</hi> What in the firſt place is called iuſtification and ſaluation by faith, that in the other is called making righteous, and raigning in life through Chriſt and him beleeued on. So alſo <hi>Acts</hi> 3.16. Firſt, (ſaith <hi>Peter) his name hath made this man ſound through faith in his name: and</hi> then <hi>the faith which is by him, hath giuen to him this diſpoſition of his body.</hi> Is it not plaine here, that faith hath healed him, is as much as his name, or Chriſt beleeued on hath healed him? the one phraſe doth expound the other.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:1709:29"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon of the point.</note>But beſide this, there are pregnant reaſons to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt this thing. Firſt, then Faith doth onely ſo iuſtifie vs, as it apprehends the righteouſneſſe of God. <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 1.</note>But Chriſt onely is the righteouſneſſe of GOD.<note place="margin">Chriſt is Gods righteouſne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e</note> Hee is <hi>Iehoua our righteouſneſſe, Ier.</hi> 33.16. <hi>the Sunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe Mal</hi> 4.2. No righteouſneſſe can ſuffice to our iuſtification, but ſuch as one as God doth ordaine and allow; nay, ſuch a righteouſneſſe as is of and in him, who is not onely man, but God alſo; for it muſt counteruaile infinite ſinnes, and ſuffice for many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands that are to be ſaued. Nor can ſuch a righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe doe vs any good, vnleſſe as it is moſt ſufficient in it ſelfe, ſo it bee made ours?<note place="margin">Whom faith onely doth make ours.</note> And where is ſuch a righteouſneſſe to be found, but in Chriſt? And how can any conceiue it otherwiſe to bee made ours, but as by faith it is apprehended of vs? Heere the Papiſts ſay that Chriſt is our righteouſneſſe<note place="margin">
                  <p>How Chriſt is our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p>Not by ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication;</p>
               </note> two waies. Firſt, becauſe he meriteth the pardon of ſinne, which is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned ours. Secondly, becauſe he worketh righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in vs. <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is very true, that Chriſt doth ſanctifie vs: notwithſtanding hee doth not make vs righteous before God, by this inherent righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For, wee are the righteouſneſſe of God, not in our ſelues (as we ſhould be, if this infuſed righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe were the matter of our iuſtification) but in him. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. And <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9.<note place="margin">But by imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> when <hi>Paul</hi> doth oppoſe the righteouſneſſe which is of Chriſt and of God, to that of the Law, which alſo he doth call his owne, as being inherent in him, hee doth cleerely ſhew that Chriſt is not our righteouſnes by that righteouſneſſe which the ſpirit doth beget in vs (for that is legall) but by another righteouſneſſe reſting in his owne
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1709:30"/> perſon, and not transfuſed, but imputed to vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 2.</note>Secondly, Faith and workes in this matter of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication are alwaies oppoſed. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8, 9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.27. But now if faith iuſtifie vs as a worke, they are not then oppoſite, but may well ſtand together.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 3.</note>Thirdly, when we ſay that faith doth ſaue, iuſtifie and purifie vs, if we vnderſtand this of the inward act of beleeuing, wee are made our owne Sauiours and ſanctifyers. For it is cleere, that wee ſaue our ſelues, when from our ſelues doth proceede that act, by and for which we are ſaued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 4.</note>Further, the leaſt true faith, though it be vnperfect doth iuſtifie. It cannot then bee, that it doth this by its owne value. For how ſhould a weake and ſmall faith, that is as a graine of muſtard ſeede, be of equall value to a greater meaſure of the ſame? when things of the ſame kinde differ in value according to their quantitie: as there is much odds in worth betweene a mite, and a maſſy wedge, though both be of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt gold. Wherefore this excellent worke of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, muſt be aſcribed vnto the thing beleeued on, that is, Ieſus Chriſt: which a ſmall and weake faith doth as truely apprehend and poſſeſſe vs of as a ſtronger.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Reaſon 5.</note>Laſtly, it was an errour which the Gnoſticks held, that their faith did iuſtifie for the excellency of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Vſes.</hi> 1. It cleereth obiections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this doctrine.</note>Firſt, this doth ſerue to cleere ſome obiections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this doctrine. For, to ſome wee ſeeme not well aduiſed, to exclude workes from iuſtification, when faith is an habite and worke of the ſoule, as is loue, and other graces of the ſpirit; and others may think that wee prize faith at too high a rate, to make it that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1709:30"/> which doth giue vs righteouſneſſe, and procure vs title to that ſuper excellent waight of glory. It vvere ſomewhat, that theſe ſay, if we did reach that faith did iuſtifie as a worke, or ſhould make faith it ſelfe our righteouſneſſe, vvhich formally doth ſo preſent vs to God. But that is farre from our minde. It is Ieſus Chriſt onely that is our righteouſneſſe: it is onely his obedience, by and for which we are righteous be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord. Faith hath no further hand and ſtroke in this weighty worke then as it doth looke to Chriſt, lay hold and poſſeſſe vs of him, that wee may haue him vvith his merits, to preſent to GOD in our behalfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. It comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the weake in faith.</note>Secondly, this doctrine doth not a little comfort thoſe that are weake in faith. Weakeneſſe of faith is a want that many of Gods people doe bewaile in themſelues; and for which they do wel-nigh deſpaire of themſelues. And it is a worthy grace, to be ſtrong in faith, as was <hi>Abraham.</hi> For by it the heart is ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed againſt all aſſaults, and is filled with peace and ioy in all eſtates: and the more our faith is, the more doe we abound in the aſſurance of our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the pardon of our ſinnes. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, let not any be out of heart, for the ſmall and ſcanty meaſure of his faith, if he haue true faith: It is not the excellencie and great meaſure of his faith that doth make him righteous before God;<note place="margin">Since faith is not our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; But Chriſt.</note> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt whom faith doth receiue and apprehend, which a weake faith can doe as well as the ſtrongeſt. Say not then my faith is weake and feeble: Is it a true and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere faith, which renouncing all other matter of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, doth depend and caſt it ſelfe on Chriſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1709:31"/> for pardon of ſinne and ſaluation? Be then of good comfort: thou art as fully and perfectly righteous before God, as he that hath the ſtrongeſt faith in the world. For thou haſt Chriſt; who is righteouſneſſe, and perfect righteouſneſſe, to euery one that doth beleeue: euen as well to him that beleeueth with a feeble faith, if a true one, as to him that beleeueth with a ſtrong faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Who is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by a weake faith as wel as a ſtrong, Euen to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Looke not then on thy faith; but conſider him, that is Ieſus Chriſt, on whom thy faith doth looke and repoſe it ſelfe, and know that he is righteouſneſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to thee. They that did looke on the Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen Serpent but with one eye, yea, but with halfe an ey, were as well and fully cured of the deadly ſtings of the fiery ſerpents, as thoſe which beheld it with both. If the Prince bee diſpoſed to beſtow on ſundry male factors their Pardon, or ſome precious Iewels vpon Beggers; they are as fully acquitted from their ſinnes, and made as rich by the poſſeſsion of that Iewell, which accept of theſe, albeit with ſhaking and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, as they that receiue them with luſty and ſtrong hands. Euen ſo is the caſe heere. Haſt thou but a dim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh faith, yet ſuch a one as doth looke vp to Chriſt, and onely to him for ſaluation? Haſt thou but a weake trembling faith, yet ſuch a one as thou doeſt reach out to receiue Chriſt that rich Pearle of heauen, and the pardon of thy ſinnes offered in him, and doeſt claſpe it about him with all thy feeble ſtrength? Make no doubt, but that thou art iuſtified in the ſight of God, doeſt ſtand clearely acquitted from all thy ſinnes, and ſhalt be healed of all their deadly ſtings. It is the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of the Iewell, not their ſtrong holding of it
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1709:31"/> that doth make thoſe beggers rich; and the Kings Pardon that doth diſcharge Malefactors from the danger of the Law, ſo they be willing to accept and pleade the ſame. And ſo it is not our ſtrong<note place="margin">Since the true poſſeſsion of him ſaueth vs, not our ſtrong hold of him,</note> or weake faith that is our righteouſneſſe, and diſcharge before God; but Ieſus Chriſt, and his obedience. This onely is required on our part, that we accept him of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vs in the Goſpell, and relye on him for full righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, and redemption; which a weake and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble faith doth as truely and entirely (if not more) as the ſtrongeſt. Nay, let mee ſay more, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of ſuch as are weake in faith: If they haue but a true deſire to beleeue,<note place="margin">He is enioyed euen by a deſire to beleeue.</note> and cannot yet in an expreſſe and explicite manner beleeue on Chriſt, they haue Chriſt, and enioy him vnto righteouſneſſe, and the pardon of their ſinnes.</p>
            <p>If a man ſhould want hands to receiue his Princes Pardon tendered to him, it would ſuffice to entitle him vnto it, and the benefit thereof, To ſhew his will to accept it; euen ſo will God in rich mercy accept in a broken and humbled ſoule a deſire to beleeue, for faith it ſelfe: and thereby ſhall they become poſſeſſed of Chriſt with all his merits, to the ſaluation of their ſoules. <hi>Bleſſed are they that hunger and thirſt for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe: for they ſhall be ſatisfied</hi> Math. 5.6.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. It accordeth grace &amp; faith in our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Laſtly, this doth ſhew how grace and faith doe well agree in our iuſtification. Workes cannot ſtand in this matter with Gods grace, as they are vrged to merit any thing toward it. For that it is not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of grace, which in the leaſt degree doth come of merit. But faith as it doth iuſtifie vs, doth bring no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of its owne to preſent to God, and to make
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1709:32"/> the beleeuer righteous, it doth chalenge nothing for its owne worth; but doth ſeeke all righteouſneſſe in Chriſt alone;<note place="margin">Since faith doth ſeeke for all from Gods grace in Chriſt.</note> doth onely take Chriſt for its righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, as he is ordained and giuen by the grace of God; doth onely preſent him, and his obedience, and plead Gods grace and mercy promiſed in him. It doth nothing derogate from the Kings grace in giuing a Pardon to his ſubiect, and from hauing the whole praiſe of his ſafety, that his ſubiect doth receiue, and plead the ſame for his life: nay, rather hereby doth the ſubiect proclaime to all men, that he hath no other meanes to ſcape the gallowes, but the gracious pardon of the King. Euen ſo faith doth not any thing obſcure Gods grace toward vs, but rather aduance it. For can a poore ſinner giue larger teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, and more amply ſet out the glory of Gods grace, then when diſclaiming himſelfe, and his beſt workes, as filthy clouts, he doth wholly flye vnto, and relye vpon Ieſus Chriſt his obedience, and Gods gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pardon of his ſinnes, by and through him? And if the life and ſafety of a Malefactor ſaued by the Kings pardon, notwithſtanding his receiuing of it, be wholly aſcribed to the grace and mercy of the Prince; how much more muſt our ſaluation, notwithſtanding that we beleeue in Chriſt be the praiſe &amp; glory of Gods rich grace? whoſe grace it is firſt to prepare and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Chriſt vnto vs, and ſaluation in him; and then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to giue vs faith (which otherwiſe wee could neuer haue) to receiue and beleeue on him.</p>
            <p>It followeth; <hi>ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting.</hi> We are now at length from the meanes come to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the benefit: which doth ſtand on two parts, as
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1709:32"/> hath beene before touched; 1. in deliuerance from that miſerable ſtate wherein we were; <hi>ſhould not periſh.</hi> 2. in conferring great good vpon vs; <hi>but haue euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life.</hi> The firſt thing that heere we may obſerue, is, what wee are before and without faith, euen loſt wretches.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 8. We are by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture loſt wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthes.</note> It is by faith in Chriſt that wee are kept from perdition: which teacheth plainely, that by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, before the Lord hath quickened vs by faith, we are all children of perdition. But of this more largely and more fitly in another place.<note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Doct.</hi> 9.</note> Secondly therefore obſerue, that though wee bee by nature dead, yet by faith we are quickened,<note place="margin">By faith we are quickned and entitled to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life.</note> and made partakers of life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. So Chriſt, verſe 36. of this chapter; <hi>Hee that beleeueth in the Sonne, hath euerlaſting life.</hi> And chapter 5.24. <hi>Verely, verely, I ſay vnto you; Hee that heareth my word, and beleeueth in him that ſent mee, hath euerlasting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but hath paſſed from death to life.</hi> And <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.3. <hi>This is eternall life, to know</hi> (that is, with the knowledge of faith) <hi>thee to bee the onely true God, and whom thou hast ſent, Ieſus Christ.</hi> For Chriſt is our life;<note place="margin">For Chriſt is our life, whom by faith we poſſeſſe.</note> 
               <hi>our life is in him, Col.</hi> 3.4. And therefore whoſoeuer do beleeue in him, haue life through and with him, As 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.11.12. From this principle we may ſee the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion to be gathered; <hi>God hath giuen vs life, and this life is in his Sonne: he that hath the Sonne hath life, he that hath not the Sonne hath not life.</hi> But to ſee this better, how by faith we come to haue life euerlaſting, we muſt conſider that we haue it either in regard of the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or of the accompliſhment and perfection. If once we bee brought to beleeue in Chriſt, life eternall is then begunne in vs;<note place="margin">1 Eternall life is by faith begun in vs,</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.38. <hi>Hee that beleeueth in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1709:33"/> mee, out of his belly ſhall there flowe riuers of water of life.</hi> And the nature of theſe waters is ſuch, that they neuer let the ſoule thirſt againe, but they are in the beleeuer a well of water ſpringing to eternall life.<note place="margin">Neuer to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.14. Neither let any man except, That they ſhall be ſo, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe a man caſt them vp againe: for that cannot bee; ſince if they could be caſt vp, how ſhould they then be a well in a man ſtill ſpringing to euerlaſting life? <hi>By faith we receiue the promiſed ſpirit. Gal.</hi> 3.14. <hi>By faith we haue Chriſt liuing in vs. Eph.</hi> 3.17. Who ſince hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dy, as the Apoſtle teacheth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.9. wee muſt not thinke that this life begunne once in any member, can vtterly bee extinguiſhed. For this life is a fruit of the ſpirit, the firſt reſurrection, a life in ſubſtance all one with that bleſſed and glorious eſtate which vvee ſhall enioy. It is an eternall life, euen for the qualitie and condition of it, and not onely by reaſon of the promiſe of God, the merit and interceſsion of Ieſus Chriſt. Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Thereby wee obtaine euen heere the fulnes of it.</note> If once we beleeue, wee alſo come to haue the fulnes of life euerlaſting, and that 2. waies, <hi>de facto,</hi> or <hi>de iure,</hi> in regard of the thing it ſelf in very deed, or in regard of right vnto it. For euery belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hath in very deed the fulnes of life &amp; glory, thogh not in himſelfe, yet in his head Chriſt Ieſus. Hee may ſay; My head Ieſus Chriſt is glorified,<note place="margin">In deed in Chriſt who is glorified for vs.</note> and I in my head ſit in heauen. Thus the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.6. <hi>God hath rayſed vs vp together, and made vs ſit in heauenly places in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> Secondly,<note place="margin">2. In right, we hauing right thereunto.</note> wee haue the accompliſhment of glory, when wee beleeue, in regard of right and propriety thereunto. When firſt wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, then we are intituled to life euerlaſting. Euen as the title to an outward inheritance followeth vpon the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1709:33"/> birth: ſo the right and hope of this kingdome doth follow our ſpirituall birth.<note place="margin">By our ſpiritual birth.</note> None that are not begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of God by water and the ſpirit ſhall enter into the kingdome. <hi>He hath begotten vs vnto an inheritance.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.4. Now the Lord begets vs his ſons &amp; daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, when he giueth vs to beleeue. For firſt, the good pleaſure of God reſteth on his naturall and onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne, on whom when we come to lay holde by faith, <hi>we are then made ſonnes. Iohn</hi> 1.12. Yea, <hi>ſons accepted. Eph.</hi> 1.6. And <hi>being ſonnes accepted, vvee are heires,</hi>
               <note place="margin">As Gods ſons and heires.</note> 
               <hi>euen ioynt-heires with Christ. Rom.</hi> 8.17. The glory of heauen is therefore called by the name of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption, becauſe it followeth thereon, and is the thing to which we are adopted. By faith therefore when we obtaine to be the ſonnes of God, wee alſo thereby ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that euerlaſting life which is to be reuealed.</p>
            <p>Which truth that wee may cleare ſomewhat bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, obſerue with me briefely theſe three things. Firſt, then, <hi>Chriſt hath merited life euerlaſting no leſſe for vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">For Chriſt hath merited it for vs.</note> 
               <hi>then righteouſnes:</hi> as <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.19.20. By the bloud of Ieſus we may be bold to enter into the holy place, by the new &amp; liuing way which he hath prepared throgh the vaile, that is, his fleſh. And <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. <hi>Through the death of the Mediatour wee which are called, receiue the promiſe of the eternall inheritance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Faith doth apprehend it alſo as well as righteouſnes.</note> faith applies and apprehendeth the one as well as the other. <hi>We are ſaued by grace through faith. Eph.</hi> 2.8. It is the Apoſtles meaning, that faith doth looke vnto, and lay holde euen of ſaluation it ſelfe, which we haue of Gods grace, as well as of any bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit tending thereunto. And if it be obiected, that hee ſpeaketh not of life euerlaſting, which is laid vp for vs
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1709:34"/> in due time to be reuealed, but of the preſent ſaluation and redemption, whereof heere wee are partakers; I anſwer: It is manifeſt in the verſe going before, what he meaneth by ſaluation; euen ſpecially the treaſures of glory: <hi>God hath raiſed vs vp together, and made vs ſit in heauenly places, &amp;c.</hi> For wee are ſaued by grace through faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Faith doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reſt vpon it, vntill wee come to enioy it.</note>Thirdly, Faith doth not onely beginne to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend it, and then leaue vs to workes that wee may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it: but faith doth ſtill apply life vnto vs, till wee are iuſtified and ſaued. <hi>By faith we ſtand and reioyce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hope of the glory of God. Rom.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Wee are kept by the power of God through faith vnto ſaluation, which is to be reuealed.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. So that our faith neuer giueth ouer, till wee haue this ſaluation, euen the end of our faith. And theſe conſiderations doe ſufficiently ſhew, that faith is it, or rather Chriſt receiued by faith, by &amp; for which we are righteous and accepted, yea, and at length attaine life euerlaſting.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The opinion of the Papiſts touching life eternall,</note>Now let vs conſider a little what is the ſentence of the Papiſts in this poynt. The Papiſts then confeſſe, that life is merited by Chriſt, and is made ours by the right of inheritance: ſo farre wee go with them. Yea, touching works they holde many things with vs, that no works of themſelues can merit life euerlaſting: 2. that works done before conuerſion can merit nothing at Gods hand,<note place="margin">and merit of works.</note> much leſſe life euerlaſting: 3. that there is no merit at Gods hand without his mercy; no exact merit, as often there is amongſt men: all theſe are true. The point whereabout wee diſſent<note place="margin">Our diſſent from th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> is, that with the merit of Chriſt and free promiſe, they vvill haue the merit of works ioined, as done by them who
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1709:34"/> are adopted children. That which directly muſt be oppoſed vnto this, is; that Gods gracious promiſing,<note place="margin">Gods grace and any merit of workes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</note> and giuing it to vs in Chriſt, cannot ſtand with the merit of our workes.</p>
            <p>And the Scripture herein is ſo euident,<note place="margin">As it is euident by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> that ſome of the Papiſts are forced to deny this coniunction of a double title vnto life eternall. For in the fourth of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> 4. the wages cannot be counted both by meere fauour, and alſo by debt and deſert: and <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.6. If it be of grace, then not of workes; for grace then were no grace. In which place obſerue this, that fauour and grace are meant and to bee taken for the rich grace of God, which is now made manifeſt in Chriſt. For otherwiſe, there is a grace which may ſtand with workes. It was grace that God did coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with man in <hi>Adam,</hi> that, had hee ſtood in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, hee ſhould haue deſerued eternall life: but the riches of grace, of meere grace, cannot abide one worke as meritorious to be coupled with it. If any, heere, except: The Apoſtle ſpeaketh of workes of the Ceremoniall Law, or done by force of nature, not by the grace of Chriſt; I anſwere, that in the firſt place,<note place="margin">Workes of grace being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from iuſtification.</note> the Apoſtle reaſons of the workes of <hi>Abraham,</hi> being now iuſtified, and euen in the flower and prime of workes.</p>
            <p>Further, we may ſee plainely, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.8, 9, 10. that grace doth exclude al works of regeneration. <hi>We are ſaued</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>by grace, not by workes.</hi> What workes? Such as are ceremoniall or done in our naturall ſtate? No, nor by workes of regeneration, euen ſuch good workes, as we are created to in Chriſt Ieſus. And marke heere the reaſon of the Papiſts. All
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1709:35"/> our workes (ſay they) come from the grace of God in vs, and are from Chriſt dwelling in vs: <hi>Ergo,</hi> it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth not the grace of God, nor Chriſts merit, that we haue them, and merit by them. Now the Apoſtle doth inferre the quite contrary. Our workes, euen our beſt workes cannot ſaue vs. Why? For they are not ours; but they are of God, whoſe workemanſhip we are, being by him created vnto them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.11, 12. And fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th and the Law being oppoſed.</note>Further, <hi>The iuſt doth liue by faith: Ergo,</hi> he cannot liue by doing. For, <hi>The Law is not of Faith.</hi> Nor is faith of the Law; neither can theſe two be conioined. As <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.18. If the inheritance be of the Law, it is no more by the promiſe: but God gaue it freely by the promiſe. Marke heere that there is ſuch oppoſition betweene workes and grace, that a thing cannot bee together a donatiue of mercy, and deſerued by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. If any thing bee ioined with Chriſt, as together meritorious of righteouſneſſe and life, it aboliſheth Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But why then doth God promiſe life euerlaſting to workes? <hi>If ye mortifie the deeds of the fleſh, yee ſhall liue. Rom.</hi> 8.13. <hi>If yee ſowe to the Spirit, you ſhall reape of the Spirit life euerlasting. Gal.</hi> 6.8.</p>
            <p>I anſwere hereunto; that there are ſome conditions<note place="margin">The conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, are not co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> merit, but ſimple con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding well with mercy.</note> ſimply conditionall, that doe well ſtand with grace. Such are thoſe conditions, whereon they onely inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding, we promiſe and vndertake to doe a matter, or beſtowe a kindneſſe on any. As, Goe with me to ſuch a place, and I will giue thee hidden treaſure. Come to me to morrow, and I wil giue thee an hundred pound. There are other conditions, which haue the reaſon of a cauſe meritorious. Such doe not onely intercede,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1709:35"/> but deſerue vpon contract as much as wee promiſe; as, Doe my worke well, and I will pay you truely. Of this kinde are thoſe conditions which are contained in the Law: <hi>Doe this, and thou ſhalt liue.</hi> As for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Goſpell, they are onely bare and ſimple conditions, which deſerue nothing; but muſt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede, and precede the beſtowing of eternall life.</p>
            <p>And heere it were worth our labour, to conſider the grounds of merit,<note place="margin">4. Grounds of the merit of workes laid by Papiſts</note> which the Papiſts lay downe in the chiefe of their arguments. They are theſe; Firſt, Chriſts Merit: Secondly, our Adoption: Thirdly, our Workes: Fourthly, Gods couenanting with vs. But none of theſe are ſufficient to eſtabliſh merit.<note place="margin">But they are falſe ones.</note> For firſt, we cannot merit as children eternall life; becauſe it is our right by birth. No child can be ſaid to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit the inheritance to which hee is borne: and how doth any merit that which is his right already? Nor doe our workes of themſelues merit; when all obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is but a witneſſe of our thankefulneſſe; nor is there any proportion betweene the duety and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance: Neither yet as they are died with the bloud of Chriſt, or doe come from his ſpirit. For, as they are of Chriſt, dwelling in vs by his ſpirit; ſo are they alſo from our ſelues, hauing a Law of ſinne dwelling in vs, and luſting againſt the ſpirit, which make them to be done imperfectly and by halues. But this (ſay they) maketh them the more meritorious, becauſe they bee done with the greater difficultie. Yea, but this is a doctrine which the Apoſtle knew not. For then hee needed not to haue cried out in that reſpect; <hi>O miſerable man that I am, &amp;c.</hi> and to flye to Chriſt that he might eſcape condemnation, as he doth, <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:1709:36"/> 7.24, 25. And for their couenant, it is not a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, binding vs to doe any thing meritorious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the obtaining of life; but onely a ſimple condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, requiring ſome thing to be done before the full fruition of glory, but well agreeing with, and no way hindering mercy.</p>
            <p>It is further obiected, that life euerlaſting is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and that rewards are deſerued.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All rewards are not due vpon, nor giuen for, deſert; there is a reward giuen by fauour.<note place="margin">Rom. 4.4. There are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of fauour as well as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert.</note> When <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>to him that worketh, the reward is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not by fauour, but by debt;</hi> doth hee not inſinuate ſo much, that ſome oft receiue euen liberall rewards onely vpon the fauour of the donour? And our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuiour ſaith: <hi>Luke</hi> 6.32. <hi>And if yee loue them that loue you, what thankes ſhall ye haue? &amp;c.</hi> The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifieth a gratuitie, as it were, and a reward of free fauour, importing thus much, that what reward men haue of God, euen vpon their beſt ſeruice, it is but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a gratuitie; no <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no debt vpon deſert.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, they ſay, that which is giuen according to workes, is deſerued by workes. But ſo is eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That indeed which is giuen according vnto workes, as the meritorious cauſes thereof, that may wel be ſaid to be deſerued by works. But now eternall life is not ſo giuen, but is beſtowed according to workes, as they are teſtimonies of our faith,<note place="margin">Workes haue a reward not as merits, but as teſtimonies of Faith.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we reſt on Chriſt, onely for our ſaluation, and for whoſe ſake onely beleeued on, they expect eternall life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>Vſes.</hi> 1. It ſheweth the prerogatiue of the faithfull:</note>Now for the vſes of this point: Firſt, it doth ſhew vs our prerogatiue that we haue by faith, and ſhould
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1709:36"/> excite vs to reioice therein; yea, to long and labour fully to enioy it. What is then the prerogatiue of ſuch as beleeue? Surely, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the Iew, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. much euery manner of way. For thereby wee are brought out of diſmall darkeneſſe, to walke in the light of Gods countenance and truth, wee are tranſlated out of the wofull condition of eternall death, to life and immortalitie; both which are brought to light for vs, to behold and enioy by the Goſpell. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. wee are made aliue to God; exalted to the dignitie of Gods ſonnes and daughters;<note place="margin">Who are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren &amp; heires of life.</note> called to the hope, yea, inueſted with ſome poſſeſsion of euerlaſting life. And are not theſe, great prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments aboue the reſidue of mankinde, who through vnbeliefe, abide ſtill in death and miſery? Are not theſe worthy dignities for earth and aſhes as wee are to attaine to? <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iohn,</hi> 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.1.) <hi>what loue the Father hath ſhewed vs, that wee ſhould be called the ſonnes of God:</hi> Yea, it is an honour and dignitie<note place="margin">Which is a great dignity.</note> ſo to be. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.12. When <hi>Saul</hi> did offer vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> to make him his ſonne, by the marriage of his daughter, it did ſeeme too high an honour for him, whoſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage was meane, for to accept. <hi>Seemeth it vnto you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>a light thing to bee a Kings ſonne in law, ſeeing I am a poore man, and of ſmall reputation.</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.23. What an vnſpeakeable dignitie is it then, that by faith wee obtaine to bee the ſonnes of the great King of heauen and earth, are made his heires, and adopted into fellowſhip of eternall life and glory, with Ieſus Chriſt? For God dealeth not with vs, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> did with his baſe ſonnes; ſo to call them vnto whom he gaue gifts, and then ſent them packing. <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:1709:37"/> 25.6. God doth not ſo turne off his faithfull ones: but he receiueth and keepeth them in his family; and admitteth to be partners in the inheritance, wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is <hi>Iſaac,</hi> euen with his Chriſt, who is the heire of all things. It is then an inheritance, that by faith we are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gotten too; and ſuch a one as is immortall, vndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and neuer fading. It is life that we obtaine; life I ſay, which of it ſelfe is moſt ſweet, chiefely to ſuch as we were, who were condemned to die, and could looke for nothing but death: and ſuch a life as is both accompanied with all fulneſſe of ioy, peace, glory and happineſſe, and ſhall alſo euer endure.</p>
            <p>Now then this being our prerogatiue, how ſhould we reioice therein?<note place="margin">Wherein we ſhould reioice.</note> And what ſhould wee more long and labour to enioy then this? <hi>Reioice not in this</hi> (ſaith our Sauiour to his Diſciples, <hi>Luke</hi> 10.20.) <hi>that ſpirits are ſubdued vnto you;</hi> but if you reioice in any thing, reioice that <hi>your names are written in heauen,</hi> and that you are appointed to liue in glory there. And truely bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi> did ſo prize this hope laid vp in heauen for him, that for it he neglected and forgate all things behinde, and did onely looke and endeauour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto this happineſſe which hee ſaw before him, following hard toward the marke, for the price of the high calling in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.13, 14. Yea, the deſire of it was ſo vehement, that it made him ſigh and groane, longing to bee clothed with this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle which is from heauen.<note place="margin">And long to enioy it in heauen.</note> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. Would not a poore begger, if he ſhould vnderſtand of ſome great and goodly liuing fallen to him in a farre countrey much reioice therein, long to goe to ſee it, and take poſſeſsion of it? And if any man ſhould offer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1709:37"/> it, would he not ſtriue with all might, and ſue for it at the law, in <hi>forma pauperis,</hi> as wee ſay, rather then goe without it? Doubtleſſe, wee haue dead and dull hearts, if wee doe not reioice in this life and glory, which by faith in Chriſt wee obtaine; if wee doe not long to take our iourney vnto heauen to haue the full fruition of it; and doe not ſtriue for it with praiers to God, &amp; ſtruggle with all our power againſt the world and Satan that would defeat vs of it. Children, for want of vnderſtanding,<note place="margin">Which wee do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not, or want of vnderſtanding</note> mind not thoſe goodly poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions they are born to; content if they haue a hobby-horſe to ride, a painted rattle, or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters to play with: And is it not of a childiſh ignorance concerning the glory of eternall life, that we ſo little minde it, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly look after it? but are well contented with theſe painted bables of the world, &amp; ſpend all our thoughts and ſtrength about them? It ſhould therefore bee our continuall praier vnto God,<note place="margin">That we are to beg of God.</note> (as <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.18.) that the eyes of our minde may bee lightened, that wee may know what is the hope of Gods calling, and what is the riches of this glorious inheritance. One cleare view of this glorious condition would rauiſh our harts with the loue of it, and excite all the powers within vs to lay holde of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">2. It teacheth vs patience in worldly loſſes and croſſes.</note>Secondly, wee may learne patience, and vvith the more quiet mindes to beare afflictions and worldly loſſes, from the contemplation of this euerlaſting life, which we haue by faith in Chriſt. <hi>Abraham</hi> did leaue his friends, his natiue country, &amp; all his earthly hopes there, which were not ſmall, and came to dwell in a ſtrange country, where he ſuſteined many grieuances by the vncircumciſed and heathniſh people, and was
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1709:38"/> exerciſed with ſundry troubles; all which hee paſſed ouer with ſingular patience, by the hope and deſire of eternall life, and that heauenly country to which hee was called. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.8.9.10.16. So likewiſe <hi>Moſes,</hi> that man of God, did quit <hi>Pharaohs</hi> court, &amp; ſet light by all the pleaſures, wealth and honours of it, chuſing aboue theſe the rebuke of Chriſt, and to ſuffer afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with Gods people. And what gaue him in theſe and all his ſufferings, encouragement? but the large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of eternall life, which he ſaw before, &amp; had reſpect vnto. <hi>Heb</hi> 11, 24, 25, 26. Finally, the faithfull Hebrewes are highly commended by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10, 32, 33, 34. for their great patience which they ſhewed in bearing afflictions, enduring reproaches, being partners with Gods perſecuted people, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering with ioy the ſpoiling of their goods: of which their patience, this was the ground, that they knewe in themſelues,<note place="margin">Since by faith we know of better things reſerued for vs.</note> how that in heauen they had a better, and an enduring ſubſtance. If a man of noble birth &amp; rich reuenue, trauailing homeward through a forraine land, ſhould there haue baſe indignities offered him, nay, ſhould fall into the hands of theeues, and by them be ſtripped of his rich apparell, and robbed of all his mony; all this would the leſſe trouble him, for that he meant to ſtay among theſe churliſh people no longer then needs hee muſt: and if hee could make ſhift for a ſeaſon, till hee came to his natiue country, that he knew himſelf there to haue friends that would honour him, and golde and ſiluer enough to ſupply this loſſe, and fully to furniſh him. Why then ſhould we fret and grieue at the baſe intreaty which wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue from worldlings? at the wrongs and reproaches
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1709:38"/> that are offered vs? at our worldly loſſes? and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly all the miſeries of this life?<note place="margin">Which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence worldly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comforts.</note> For haue not we an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly home, and an eternall life by Chriſt prepared for vs? at the which if wee once arriue, wee know by faith that there we haue friends, euen God, his Saints and Angels, who will honour vs, riches and treaſures ineſtimable to ſtore vs, ioy and glory vnſpeakeable to refreſh vs.<note place="margin">Thou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rld<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch caſes whine not without c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> leeſing their worldly comforts, lee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> all.</note> None would thinke it ſtrange to ſee a poor man that did carry al his treaſure about him, to whine and cry, if falling into the hands of theeues hee did at once leeſe all; for hee is cleane vndone, and hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left to ſuccour him: but it were extreame baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in a wealthy man to take on for the loſſe of ſome ſmall ſummes, when it is well knowne, that hee hath thouſands at home that are ſafe and entire. Thus for worldly men, wee may well allow them to chafe and fret, howle and cry at the loſſe of their outward peace, wealth, mirth, honor and reputation. For (alas!) how can they doe otherwiſe? they are become ſtarke beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; are cleane vndone; haue nothing left; nor know not whence to looke for a ſupply: but truely Gods people doe too too bad ſhame their profeſsion, who in outward afflictions and loſſes grow impatient, and are out of hart; whoſe loſſes are nothing to that which is left them, and whoſe hopes, which are in heauen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued for them, will abundantly recompenſe all the miſeries of this life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">3. It ſtaieth our hart in worldly cares &amp; feares.</note>Thirdly, This doth ſerue to eſtabliſh our hearts againſt ſundry worldly cares and feares: we are in reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe maner toſſed in our ſelues, &amp; diſtracted hither &amp; thither, one while affecting earthly greatnes &amp; abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; another while carking for earthly neceſſaries,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1709:39"/> and fearing the want of them: But all without cauſe. For what neede wee ſo admire at,<note place="margin">For we need <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> heauenly, which are better, meant vs.</note> and aſpire vnto the glory and happineſſe of this life, who haue an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life? that hath moſt excellent glory, riches, and happineſſe ioined with it, prepared and giuen vs through faith in Chriſt. Is it not a baſe minde in a man, that is owner, or at leaſt heire, of moſt ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſtately palaces, to couet the poore cottages of beggers, that ſtand by the high way ſide, and repine if he cannot get them? What will ſatisfie vs, if hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and etenall life cannot? Doubtleſſe, <hi>Dauid</hi> made account, that in this poſſeſsion, he was as well as heart could wiſh. <hi>The lines</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.6.) <hi>are fallen vnto me in pleaſant places: yea, I haue a faire heritage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So alſo is it very ſtrange, to ſee a godly man toile and moile for earthly matters, in feare of want. <hi>Feare not, little flocke: for it is your Fathers pleaſure to giue you a Kingdome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Not doubt of earthly neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, when God hath giuen vs an heauenly kingdome.</note> ſaith Chriſt. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. What is it that we are bid not to feare? The want of foode, raiment, and earthly neceſſaries, which are mentioned in the former verſes. And why? Becauſe our Father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen doth meane vs a kingdome. For, what? hath God prepared an eternall life for vs, and will he not main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this temporall? Hath he purchaſed heauen, and the glory of it for vs, and will hee ſee vs periſh for want of earthly things? There is not any earthly father, that doth with great ſummes of money, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe large poſſeſsions for his ſonne, and meaneth to beſtow on him his whole eſtate, who will neglect to finde him with foode and raiment, and giue him ſuch maintenance as is fitting. Perhaps he will keepe him ſomewhat ſhort during his nonage, and not let him
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1709:39"/> haue his purſe alway full of money, for his idle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes, vntill he haue wit how to lay it out, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage ſo great an eſtate: So heere, God doth not giue to his children outward things, alway in that fulneſſe that they deſire, becauſe they haue not vnderſtanding in this their nonage to diſpoſe of them; and it might be dangerous to feede their humours: but if by faith we can once ſee that he hath meant vs his kingdome, and appointed eternall life for vs; it is foule diſtruſt to doubt that hee will forſake vs, and put vs to our ſhifts, for our earthly neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">4. It is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citement to faith.</note>Fourthly, it muſt excite vs highly to prize faith, and make vs looke about to get faith, and how to grow in it; <hi>Peter</hi> (1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7.) calleth faith a precious thing, yea, much more precious then gold. And ſurely, there is not a more precious iewell in the world then it is: by which we obtaine Chriſt, and all his riches;<note place="margin">As by which we obtaine ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation in Chriſt.</note> are drawn out of deaths dungeon, quickened with a ſpirituall, and intereſſed in eternall life. It is not all the gold of America, nor Rubies of the Ocean, that can doe this for vs: No, there is no other grace of the Spirit, but faith which can help vs to this benefit, poſſeſſe vs of Chriſt, and entitle vs to heauen. For as we can onely ſee the light of the Sunne with the eye, and take our foode with the mouth; ſo is it faith onely,<note place="margin">And that onely.</note> by which we can ſee Ieſus Chriſt, and enioy him for our righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe vnto life. Yea,<note place="margin">Which is its ſpeciall dignity aboue other graces.</note> there is more moment in a weake faith to our ſaluation, then all other graces, though they were perfect in vs. Light and heate can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſeparated in the Sunne: Nor can faith, loue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and other graces, be found ſingle in a godly ſoule. But had a man perfect repentance, knowledge
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1709:40"/> and loue, theſe could not ſaue him, if there were not faith, to apprehend Chriſt for his ſatisfaction and a propitiation for his ſinnes. A dimme eye to looke on the Brazen Serpent, was of more auaile to a poore <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite</hi> ſtung with a fiery ſerpent, then the vſe of all his other members. For what would the ſwiftneſſe of his feete, ſtrength of ſinewes, nimbleneſſe of hands, &amp;c. ſtand him heere in ſtead, if he had not an eye to looke on the Brazen Serpent? So without faith we lye dead in ſinnes, and cannot but periſh of the mortall ſtings which Satan hath giuen: It it onely faith in Chriſt that can cure our ſoules of them, and make vs heere to liue vnto God, and hereafter in all happineſſe with him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:1709:40"/>
            <head>A Pillar, erected on the Graue, and inſcribed, to the deere memory of that learned and godly Diuine, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. PAVL BAINE. By I. E.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>SOme Men in ſhape, are Diuels: and other ſome,</l>
               <l>Mis-ſhapen monſters, we may truely ſay:</l>
               <l>Brute beaſts full oft in humane ſhape doe come,</l>
               <l>Whom carnall ſenſe and furious rage doth ſway.</l>
               <l>The forme and name of Men many retaine,</l>
               <l>That come farre ſhort of the right humane ſtraine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Againe: Some babes are demy-men, I know;</l>
               <l>In whom of man ſome ruder lines appeare:</l>
               <l>But to mans ſtature few there are that grow,</l>
               <l>Or the ripe nature of a man doe beare.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In troupes of men, to finde</hi> a Man <hi>at Noon</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>(With Torch-light)</hi> were a taske not eaſily doon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Aye me! (deare <hi>Baine</hi>) what treaſure then we had</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt thou amongſt vs didſt aliue remaine!</l>
               <l>And by thy death (which good men made ſo ſad)</l>
               <l>What loſſe vnvalued doe we now ſuſtaine!</l>
               <l>Ah, harmefull Death! what Age ſhall vs requite</l>
               <l>So great a dammage, and ſo foul deſpite!</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:1709:41"/>
               <l>Deere worthy <hi>Baine,</hi> a man complete to be,</l>
               <l>And more then any one meere man, I finde.</l>
               <l>The vertues, which in moſt we <hi>ſingle</hi> ſee,</l>
               <l>As choyſe Ingredients were in him <hi>combin'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Him to ſet forth; though made of humane bloud,</l>
               <l>A rich <hi>Pandera</hi> of diuineſt good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Rare is a faithfull, zealous Chriſtian:</l>
               <l>More rare, good conſcience and great learning meet.</l>
               <l>One, of a thouſand, proues a godly man.</l>
               <l>A learned Scribe; a skilfull, a diſcreete,</l>
               <l>A watchfull Paſtour; Teacher excellent;</l>
               <l>Such who can finde? vnleſſe <hi>Paul Baine</hi> be meant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There was in him a blameleſſe innocence,</l>
               <l>A feruent zeale, ſound iudgement, pearcing wit,</l>
               <l>Not vulgar learning, moouing eloquence,</l>
               <l>An vnderſtanding of deepe points, to it</l>
               <l>An hart high-mounted, farre aboue the sky;</l>
               <l>Yet low as earth, in true humility.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Death! I nere ſhould ceaſe of thee to plaine,</l>
               <l>Who of ſuch treaſure haſt vs now bereft;</l>
               <l>Did not our loſſe turne to his greater gaine,</l>
               <l>And had he not a world vnthankefull left;</l>
               <l>Which ſets at nought (as droſſe and baſeſt Mine)</l>
               <l>Moſt precious Pearls, and of the brighteſt ſhine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Worthy <hi>Eliſha,</hi> when thy Maſter deere</l>
               <l>In flaming coach was rapt vp vnto God,</l>
               <l>Thou did'ſt obtaine, that (O thou happy Seer!)</l>
               <l>His <hi>doubled ſpirit</hi> on thee might make abode.</l>
               <l>Oh! well were mee, if ſo within my breſt</l>
               <l>But <hi>halfe the ſpirit</hi> of this bleſt Saint might reſt.</l>
               <byline>I. E.</byline>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:1709:41"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
